<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Antidote against purgatory. Or discourse, wherein is shewed that good-workes, and almes-deeds, performed in the name of Christ, are a chiefe meanes for the preuenting, or migatating the torments of purgatory. Written by that vertuous, and rightworthy gentle-woman (the honour of her sexe for learning in England) Ms. Iane Owen, late of God-stow, in Oxfordshire, deceased, and now published after her death</title>
            <author>Owen, Jane, of God-stow.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1634</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 180 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 154 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08680</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18984</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103135</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838892</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838892</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3282</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08680)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3282)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1212:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Antidote against purgatory. Or discourse, wherein is shewed that good-workes, and almes-deeds, performed in the name of Christ, are a chiefe meanes for the preuenting, or migatating the torments of purgatory. Written by that vertuous, and rightworthy gentle-woman (the honour of her sexe for learning in England) Ms. Iane Owen, late of God-stow, in Oxfordshire, deceased, and now published after her death</title>
                  <author>Owen, Jane, of God-stow.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 276 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>English College Press],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Saint-Omer :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed M.DC.XXXIIII. [1634]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer from STC.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through; some pages marked and stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Salvation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Purgatory --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3282:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANTIDOTE AGAINST PVRGATORY. OR Diſcourſe, wherein is ſhewed that <hi>Good-Workes,</hi> and <hi>Almes-deeds,</hi> performed in the Name of Chriſt, are a chiefe meanes for the preuenting, or mitigating the Torments of Purgatory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by that Vertuous, and Right worthy Gentle-woman (the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of her Sexe for Learning in England) M<hi rend="sup">s</hi>. IANE OWEN, late of</hi> God-ſtow, <hi>in</hi> Oxford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire, <hi>deceaſed, and now publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed after her death.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>As VVater doth extinguish Fier: ſo Almes-deeds do extinguish ſinne.</p>
               <bibl>Eccleſ. 3.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed M.DC.XXXIIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:3282:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3282:2"/>
            <head>TO THE VVORTHY AND CONSTANT CATHOLICKES OF ENGLAND: And more particularly, to ſuch, who be of the beſt temporall Meanes.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>ORTHY and Noble Catholiks:</hi> My charity towards the aduancing of the ſpiritual good of your ſoules, <pb facs="tcp:3282:3"/> is the mayne Allectiue, inuiting me to write this ſmall Treatiſe, (pardon I pray the boldnes of my Sexe heerin.) The ſubiect ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is, First, to inculcate, &amp; make deep impreſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in your minds, of the horrour, and most dreadfull torments of <hi>Purgatory:</hi> Secon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darily, to ſet before your eyes, the best meanes to preuent, at least to aſſwage, and mitigate them: <hi>gratu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> opus agricolis;</hi> A labour (I hope) pleaſing to ſuch, who are deſirous to cultiuate their owne Soules, for gayning their ſpirituall and expected haruest.</p>
            <p>That you belieue there is a <hi>Purgatory,</hi> your owne Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Faith teacheth you; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <pb facs="tcp:3282:3"/> preſuming that you reſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moueable therein, without the least fluctuation of iudgment, I hould it were but lost labour, to ſpend any tyme in prooffe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Only I heere couet, that you would deeply conſider and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate thereof; and thereupon that you would withall meditate and put in practiſe the meanes of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoiding the ſame.</p>
            <p>Touching the terriblenes of the Torments of <hi>Purgatory,</hi> I haue inſiſted in the Authority of the most Bleſſed <hi>Cardinall Bellarmine;</hi> out of one of whoſe ſpirituall bookes I haue tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a whole paſſage concerning this ſubiect, as hereafter I shall <pb facs="tcp:3282:4"/> more fully shew. Thus I make him the foundation or ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke of this my enſuing Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; and the rest following I do build, and erect vpon this foundation: ſo as this <hi>Miſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lene worke</hi> of myne, may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps reſemble the statua of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchodonozor,</hi> of which, part was gould, part ſiluer, and part of baſer mettall. So I am ſure, that what is taken out of the learned Cardinalls writings in this my Treatiſe, is perfect gould or ſiluer; what is adioyned there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to by me, must (I willingly yield) endure the touch of the learned, to proue what mettall it is.</p>
            <p>But now, to proceede a little <pb facs="tcp:3282:4"/> further: I could wish you <hi>(wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Catholickes)</hi> that you would haue a feeling apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the paynes of <hi>Purgatory,</hi> though yet to come. True it is, that the <hi>Time preſent,</hi> and the <hi>Time future</hi> are in nature dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent; yet if a man could in ſome caſe, ſo liuely paint to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the face of the <hi>Time fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> as that it might appeare to him, to be the <hi>Time preſent,</hi> it were, <hi>felix Error,</hi> a happy mistaking or confuſion of tymes, (to vſe the Catholike Churches like
<hi>Dialect</hi> of the ſinne of <hi>Adam,</hi> calling it, <hi>felix Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa:</hi>) For then would men ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehende the Future paynes of <pb facs="tcp:3282:5"/>
               <hi>Purgatory,</hi> as preſent, (and certainely once they muſt be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent;) and conſequently, would have a greater feare and dread of them, then co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly they now haue. It is not in mans power to depriue God of his incommum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable Attribute of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> being euen of the Eſsence of God.</p>
            <p>This then being ſo, why will you not ſeeke to appeaſe this his <hi>Iuſtice</hi> in this world, when ſmall ſatiſfactions will ſerue, rather then to performe thoſe ſatisfactions incomparably far greater in a more horrible man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, in the next world, by endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thoſe Torments, which are not to be endured? And there to <pb facs="tcp:3282:5"/> endure them,
<hi>donec reddas nouiſſimum Quadrantem, Matth. 5.</hi> Theſe are the words of holy Scripture, and are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood in the iudgment of the Ancient Fathers, of a Soule ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>Purgatory,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore must be performed: which forcing words, ſince they ought to be most dreadfull to ech Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke, not performing his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction in this life, I haue therefore thought not amiſſe (though I grant in a most vnu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall manner) to ſet downe in the lower part of euery page; that whereſoeuer the Reader ſhall open theſe few leaues, his eye shall instantly meete with the <pb facs="tcp:3282:6"/> ſaid moouing words, thereby to cauſe him to haue a more intenſe and ſerious meditation of them.</p>
            <p>It is certaine, that God is pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully cruell (as I may ſay) ſince he is content to turne Eternity of punishments, into temporall paines; But withall it is no leſſe certaine, that a ſoule not perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming its penance in this life be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore its diſſolution from the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, can no more immediatly aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend to Heauen, then the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs</hi> which dyed in
<hi>Egypt,</hi> could be buryed in the land <hi>of Promiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well now, the chiefest help for the preuenting of the paines of
<hi>Purgatory,</hi> is the practiſe of <pb facs="tcp:3282:6"/> 
               <hi>Workes</hi> of
<hi>Almes-deeds,</hi> and ſuch other actions of Mercy, as hereafter in this ſhort Treatiſe wil more fully be proued. Workes of this nature are the only Oyle, which is to be powred into a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting ſoule, whoſe full ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for its former ſinnes, is not yet accompliſhed.</p>
            <p>Gods ſacred Word aſsureth you, that you may buy Heauen with
<hi>Good Workes: Venite poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dete paratum vobis regnum; Eſuriuienim, &amp; dediſtis ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducare &amp;c<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Matth. 25.</hi> Much more then, may you with <hi>Good Workes</hi> (dyed in the bloud of our Sauiour, and not otherwiſe) buy out the paynes of <hi>Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi> 
               <pb facs="tcp:3282:7"/> And though you do find a reluctation in your naturall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions to relinquiſh a part of your state to that end, now in your lyfe time; yet let that be made eaſy to you by <hi>Grace,</hi> which is hard and difficult by
<hi>Nature;</hi> that ſo it may be ſaid of you, as was ſaid of
<hi>Cornelius</hi> the Centurion, <hi>Act. 10. Elee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſinae veſtrae commemora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae ſunt in conſpectu Dei.</hi> For aſſure your ſelues, that the Grace of God euer ſeeketh a charitable Hart.</p>
            <p>And by this meanes, you may become more rich in your graues, then you could haue beene in your life tyme: Since to giue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way <pb facs="tcp:3282:7"/> riches, in a mans lyfe, for the good of the ſoule, is to carry them away after his death. And in this ſenſe, they hould most, who haue the most open hand in diſpenſing of their riches; So true is that ſentence, to wit,
<hi>It is no ſmall riches, for Gods ſake, to abandon riches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But (alas) ſuch are the pit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tifull tymes, wherein we liue, &amp; ſuch is the ſcarſity of Vertue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs, as that insteed of pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſing <hi>Workes</hi> of Charity, men are commended and prayſed, if only they forbeare to practiſe workes of Iniustice and Wrong. And thus we are glad to accept of a meere <hi>Priuation</hi> of <hi>Vice,</hi> 
               <pb facs="tcp:3282:8"/> in place of a <hi>Poſitiue,</hi> and <hi>reall Vertue.</hi> O the miſerablenes of our dayes! The very Beasts do not, nor can ſinne, nor can they do any wrong; are they there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vertuous?</p>
            <p>Well, I humbly beſecch you to haue a ſetled eye vpon your ſoules good, for the preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of future puniſhments; and remember, that our Sauiour in the Ghoſpell <hi>(Luc. 17.)</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended the <hi>vniuſt Steward</hi> for hoording vp for the tyme to come; and ſhall then the ſlouth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full careleſſnes of Catholikes be vpbrayded with that <hi>vniuſt ſtewards</hi> diligence? God forbid! But before I do remit you to the
<pb facs="tcp:3282:8"/> peruſall of this enſuing Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, I will put you in mind, that all <hi>Good Workes</hi> streame from <hi>Charity,</hi> &amp; that without it, there are no <hi>Good Workes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, how neceſsary and effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacious <hi>Charity</hi> is in its owne Nature, it being the Queene of all vertues (the which who hath it, cannot be damned, and who wanteth, cannot be ſaued) I will not only refer you to the
<hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> iust prayſes giuen thereof <hi>(1. Cor. 8.)</hi> but alſo to the learned and graue Iudgment of <hi>Cardinall Bellarmine</hi> herein, who thus writeth <hi>(lib. 5. de ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terna Felicitate cap. 6.) Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deo dicere, ſi oleum charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis <pb facs="tcp:3282:9"/> in animas damnatorum &amp;c. I dare be bould to ſay, that if the oyle of Charity could diſtill downe into the ſoules of damned men, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Diuells, we inſtantly ſhould behould, both the damned Soules and the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uells, to aſcend out of their torments. As on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſide, if this oyle of Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhould forſake the holy Angels, Apoſtles, Martyrs, Virgins, &amp;c. they inſtantly would become lumpiſh and heauy, &amp; thereupon would deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d into the loweſt parts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you ſee, what this lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Cardinall</hi> cenſureth here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. <pb facs="tcp:3282:9"/> Do not then ſleight and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect the worth of this Noble Vertue of <hi>Charity;</hi> and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly the moſt healthfull and fruitfull effects, proceeding from thence; I meane <hi>Good Workes, Mercy,</hi> and pious Liberality im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed vpon others; aſcertayning your ſelues, that the next and most ſpeedy helpe to procure God, to be mercifull, in mildly chastizing the relickes of your ſinnes, &amp; to mitigate your tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall puniſhments, is to ſhew your ſelues mercifull to others; <hi>Beati miſericordes, quoniam ipſi miſericordiam conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentur, Matth. 5.</hi> I meane prompt and ready in exerciſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng <pb facs="tcp:3282:10"/> the <hi>Workes of Charity;</hi> ſince ſiluer in a large degree bestowed in this manner, is the ſpirituall Water, which quencheth the fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of <hi>Purgatory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One thing heere I wish you to remember, that euery man (how yong ſoeuer) through the wingy ſpeedines of timc, is euen flying towards his graue. And when he is once thither come, then hath he bidden his last
<hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieu,</hi> or <hi>Good Night</hi> to all the world. Therefore whiles the day lasteth, employ your ſelues buſily in Good Workes: So true (and withall wholeſome) is that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell in Holy Writ. <hi>Eccl. 9. Quodcumque facere poteſt <pb facs="tcp:3282:10"/> manus tua, inſtanter operare &amp;c. Whatſoeuer thy hand can do, do it inſtantly; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe neither any worke, nor reaſon, nor knowledge, nor wiſdome, is beneath whither thou haſteſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And with this <hi>(Worthy &amp; deare Catholickes)</hi> I remit you to the peruſing of this litle Treatiſe; Humbly beſeeching his Mercy, that the reading of it may beget great and worthy ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects in you; And then I shall hope, that you will vouchſafe me now and then, your charitable prayers; not only for the remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the guilt of eternall dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, due for my infinite ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes; <pb facs="tcp:3282:11"/> but alſo, if ſo his <hi>Diuine Maieſty</hi> would vouchſafe me, (though moſt vnworthy) ſo much fauour and grace, that I may eſcape this most dreadfull fyer of
<hi>Purgatory.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Soules well-wiſhing Admoniſher, IANE OVVEN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:3282:11"/>
            <head>The Contents of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall Sections en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing.</head>
            <list>
               <label>SECT. I.</label>
               <item>OF the inexplicable paynes of <hi>Purgatory,</hi> and of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Circumſtances accompany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame paynes; tranſlated out of the ſpirituall Booke of <hi>Cardinall Bellarmine,</hi> inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled; <hi>De gemitu Columbae</hi> lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>9.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>SECT. II.</label>
               <item>Of the meanes to auoyde, at least to mitigate, the paynes of
<hi>Purgatory.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3282:12"/>
                  <hi>SECT. III.</hi>
               </label>
               <item>A perſuaſory Diſcourſe, for the putting in practiſe the meanes (which are <hi>Good Workes</hi>) for the auoyding the paynes of
<hi>Purgatory.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>SECT. IV.</label>
               <item>Certaine examples of <hi>Good Workes,</hi> to be practiſed for the auoyding of <hi>Purgatory,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded by the Authour of this Treatiſe.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:3282:12"/>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Non exibis inde, donec reddas nouiſsimum Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drantem.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 27.</bibl>
               <p>Thou shalt not goe out from thence, till thou repay the laſt Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <pb facs="tcp:3282:13"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Date Eleemoſynam, &amp; ecce omnia vobis munda ſunt.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 11. <hi>v.</hi> 41.</bibl>
               <p>Giue Almes, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hould all thinges are cleane vnto you.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3282:13"/>
               <head>Of the inexplicable paynes of Purgatory, and of other Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances accompanying the ſame; tranſlated out of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Booke of Cardinall Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine, entituled: <hi>De ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitu Columbae. lib. 2. ca.
9. THE I. SECTION.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>MONG all the Paſſions of the mind, there is not any, which hath ſo great a ſoueraignty, and <pb n="2" facs="tcp:3282:14"/> command ouer man, as the Paſſion of <hi>Feare.</hi> The reaſon hereof is euident, and euen ingraffed in mans Nature. For euery man taketh plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and delight in a ſweet and quiet repoſe of his owne beeing; and conſequently flyeth, and auoydeth what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer may endanger to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, or take away his ſaid quietneſſe and rſt; accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that Axiome in Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy: <hi>Omnis res cupit con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruare ſuum Eſſe.</hi> And here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon it ryſeth, that the <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> of <hi>Loue</hi> is nothing ſo po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tent and preuayling with men, as <hi>Feare.</hi> For we expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimentally
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3282:14"/> ſee, that moſt men are afrayd to commit diuers impieties, more for <hi>Feare</hi> of puniſhment to be inflicted by the Law, then for <hi>Loue</hi> of God, or Vertue.</p>
               <p>Now, to apply this to my preſent purpoſe. Whereas my proiect in theſe enſuing leaues is, to awaken the harts and minds of diuers Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liks for the preuenting, or at leaſt leſſening the paynes of
<hi>Purgatory</hi> by their <hi>good deeds</hi> and workes of Charity, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in their lyfe tyme; therefore I haue in the Front of this Treatiſe thought good to plant a Diſcourſe tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching <pb n="4" facs="tcp:3282:15"/> the incomprehenſible torments of <hi>Purgatory,</hi> and other circumſtances accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paning the ſame torments; that ſo, ſuch perſons, for whoſe ſake this labour is vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dertaken, (as not being blindfoulded vnder the veile of careleſſe negligence) may haue a greater <hi>Feare</hi> &amp; Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of the ſaid torments; and conſequently, may be more watchfull and ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous for their preuenting of them, by their Almes-deeds, and other ſuch workes of Charity.</p>
               <p>Which kind of <hi>Feare</hi> was (as I may tearme it) the
<hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> 
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:3282:15"/> of Reuerend <hi>Antiquity,</hi> cauſing the liuers in thoſe ancient times, to be ſo dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full not only of the torments of Hell, but euen of <hi>Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry:</hi> So healthfull to mans Soule is that admonition of Holy Writ, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. <hi>Walke you in feare, during the tyme of your earthly habitation.</hi> And vpon this ground our For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers labored ſo much to ſpread themſelues in the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of good works; and this with moſt iuſt reaſon; ſince he <hi>is truly rich, who is rich in good-workes: and the want of them is a ſpirituall beggary.</hi> And therfore moſt deſerued<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <pb n="6" facs="tcp:3282:16"/> is this <hi>Feare</hi> ſtiled by the Wiſeman, <hi>The beginning of Wiſdome, Prou.</hi> 11. as alſo by ſome others, <hi>The Mother, &amp; Daughter of wiſdome;</hi> and ſo holy Iob had iuſt reaſon to ſay: <hi>I feared all my works. Iob.</hi> 9.</p>
               <p>The Diſcourſe prefixed touching the Paynes of
<hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory,</hi> I haue wholy taken, and Tranſlated out of one of the ſpirituall Bookes of the moſt Worthy <hi>Cardinall Bellarmine,</hi> entituled: <hi>De Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitu Columbae. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>chap.</hi> 9. Therefore when the Reader peruſeth it, let him remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that it is
<hi>Bellarmyne</hi> who ſpeaketh, not I. In this paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3282:16"/> the learned <hi>Cardinall</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lateth certaine dogmaticall Miracles, touching the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Purgatory.</hi> I haue thought it much more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayling to deliuer the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents therof in the
<hi>Cardinalls</hi> owne words, which are without any affectation of Oratory, or fyled Speach, then by any other meanes or Method of my owne, in al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering the ſame. Since I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, that the ſpeaches of ſo worthy, ſo learned, ſo pious a man (being an Ornament of this preſentage) will ſway more with all good Catho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liks, by way of perſwaſion, <pb n="8" facs="tcp:3282:17"/> then any words of myne can effect; And certaine it is, that <hi>who ſpeaketh perſwading<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſpeaketh Eloquently.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And I hould it a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Honour, to become a poore Tranſlator of any part of his learned writings, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therby the more good; then to be accounted a skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Compoſer of Bookes, doing therin the leſſer good. And with this I refer the Reader to the paſſage of <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmyne</hi> by me Tranſlated, wiſhing him not to be diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of the truth of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents thereof; ſeeing he may ſee, that the <hi>Cardinall</hi> giueth
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3282:17"/> full credit and aſſent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; and alſo, in that he is an ouer <hi>Materiall</hi> and <hi>Senſible Christian</hi> (as I may tearme him) who meaſures matters of Fayth and Religion, by the falſe yard of naturall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion. And great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credulity and dulnes it is, to thinke of things touching the ſoule, only as he ſeeth them, abſtracting them from the trutination of Gods Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice heere-after to come; themſelues thus through ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine heedleſnes falling vpon that dangerous ſentence of the Wiſeman: <hi>Ita ſecuri vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uunt, quaſi Iustorum facta habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3282:18"/> Eccleſ.</hi> 8. They liue as ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely, as if their workes were of the Iuſt. But what doth there immediatly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low? <hi>Hoc vaniſsimum.</hi> This is moſt vayne.</p>
               <div n="purgatory" type="discourse">
                  <head>The diſcourſe of Cardinall Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine, touching the inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicable paynes of Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory.</head>
                  <p>THoſe Soules, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne in <hi>Purgatory,</hi> do afford to vs yet liuing in the world, a great occcaſion &amp; matter of teares; in ſo much that a due conſideration &amp; meditation of <hi>Purgatory</hi> may
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3282:18"/> iuſtly be termed a flowing well of teares.</p>
                  <p>Now touching the paynes of <hi>Purgatory,</hi> foure principall heades or branches are to be conſidered; from the which we may in part coniecture of the greatnes of thoſe pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes; and in regard of ſuch their greatnes, all good men may be the more eaſily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, to powre out their teares in commiſeration of their Chriſtian Brethren, who are in the meane tyme torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted with thoſe paines.</p>
                  <p>The firſt of theſe Heades is, that the paynes of
<hi>Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory are greater &amp; more intenſe, <pb n="12" facs="tcp:3282:19"/> then any paynes, which men can ſuffer in this lyfe.</hi> The ſecond, that the paynes of Purgatory to them that ſuffer them, <hi>do for the most part endure longer, then any paynes of this life can endure.</hi> The third, that the
<hi>ſoules which lye in Purgatory, cannot helpe, or bring any eaſe to themſelues.</hi> The fourth and laſt Head is, that <hi>the ſoules which are in Purgatory, are of huge number, and almost infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite in number.</hi> Now from all theſe different paſſages, it is cleare, that the ſoules in
<hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory</hi> are in a pittifull ſtate, and therefore moſt worthy of all commiſeration; &amp; that <pb n="13" facs="tcp:3282:19"/> thoſe men, who yet are li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uing, are no leſſe then half mad and diſtracted in iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, who during their life tyme, are careleſſe and negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in ſatisfying for their ſinnes, and had rather deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend (vpon their death) to thoſe places of Torments, then to be depryued of any pleaſure, while they liue in this world.</p>
                  <p>And now to begin with the firſt, which is, that the paynes of <hi>Purgatory</hi> are grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and more violent then all paynes ioyned together, which in this lyfe we can vndergoe; this verity is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3282:20"/> by the authority of <hi>S. Austin in Pſal.</hi> 37. who thus writeth hereof: <hi>Domine, ne in indignatione tua arguas me &amp;c. O Lord do not chastice me in thy wrath and indignation; Let me not be in the number of thoſe, to whom thou shalt ſay; Ite in ignem aeternum, go into euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting fyer; neither otherwiſe correct me in thy anger, but that I may be made ſuch, as that my ſaid correction shall not be need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to be increaſed with that purging fyer, in reſpect of ſuch men, qui ſalui erunt, ſic tamen quaſi per ignem, who ſhalbe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, but as by fyer.</hi> And then a litle after <hi>S. Austin</hi> thus fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3282:20"/> inlargeth himſelfe: <hi>Et quia dicitur ſaluus erit, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temnitur ille ignis &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>becauſe it is ſayd in the place a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, they shalbe ſaued, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that fyer is neglected and litle feared. True it is, they shalbe ſaued by fyer: grauior tamen erit ille ignis</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>quàm quicquid potest homo pati in hac vita: Notwithſtanding that fyer shalbe more heauy and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable, then any paynes, which a man can ſuffer in this lyfe. And you well know, what great torments diuers wicked men haue here ſuffered, and are able to ſuffer; yea good and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous men haue ſuffered as much <pb n="16" facs="tcp:3282:21"/> as the former. For what paynes or torments hath any malefa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctour, theefe, adulterer, or any other wicked or ſacrilegious per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon ſuffered, which Martyrs haue not ſuffered for their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion of Christ?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Therefore theſe Torments, which are in this world, are of a far more lower degree: And neuertheleſſe, you ſee, how rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and prepared men stand to performe any thing commanded them, to preuent the ſuffering of them; with how much more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon then haue men to doe that, which God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeth them, that ſo they may not vndergoe thoſe (by many degrees more horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) <pb n="17" facs="tcp:3282:21"/> torments?</hi> Thus far <hi>S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin,</hi> whoſe iudgment herein many other Fathers follow.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Saint Gregory</hi> thus dila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of the ſame point:
<hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mine, ne in furore tuo arguas me &amp;c. Lord, do not chastice me in thy fury, nor rebuke me in thy anger. I know well, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the end of this lyfc ſome mens ſinnes shalbe expiated &amp; purged by the flames of Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory; others shall vndergoe the ſentence of eternall damnation. Neuertheleſſe, becauſe I do firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly belieue, that tranſitory fyer to be more inſufferable, then any tribulation in this world; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I thirst not only not to be <pb n="18" facs="tcp:3282:22"/> abandoned and remitted to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall damnation; but alſo I great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly feare, to be chastized in this temporall punishment of Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory.</hi> Thus much <hi>S. Gregory.</hi> Of the ſame iudgment here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, are Venerable <hi>Bede, in</hi> 3. <hi>Pſal Poenit. S. Anſelme, in cap.</hi> 3. <hi>Ep.</hi> 1 <hi>ad Cor. S. Bernard de obi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu Humberti &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>S. Thomas of Aquin l.</hi> 4. <hi>ſent. d.</hi> 30.
<hi>q.</hi> 1. <hi>art.</hi> 2. doth not only ſubſcribe to the iudgment of the former Fathers in this point; but he alſo further maintayneth, that the leaſt payne in <hi>Purgatory</hi> is greater &amp; more inſupportable, then the greateſt torment in this <pb n="19" facs="tcp:3282:22"/> world; And yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all this, we obſerue daily, that men are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayd to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temne thoſe moſt inſufferable torments in <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory,</hi> who cannot endure far leſſe paines in this world. But this is the blindnes of mans corruption, which is much to be deplored in this our vale of Teares.</p>
                  <p>To proceed further. <hi>S. Thomas</hi> proueth this his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſentence and iudgment from this following reaſon: It is (ſayth he) an inexpug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable and vndeniable truth, that <hi>poena damni,</hi> the payne of the loſſe, incurred by <pb n="20" facs="tcp:3282:23"/> ſinne, is far more grieuous, then <hi>Poena ſenſus,</hi> then any payne of ſenſe, or feeling. And it is further moſt eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and confeſſed, that all thoſe, who are in <hi>Purgatory,</hi> during their ſtay theſe, do ſuffer
<hi>Poenam damni,</hi> the paine of loſſe; that is, the loſſe of the viſion of God.</p>
                  <p>But to auoyde the force of this Reaſon, it may be perhaps replyed by ſome, that the perpetuall puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of loſſe, to wit, to loſe for all eternity the ſight of God (as ſuch ſuffer, who are in Hell) is truly indeed a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment and the greateſt of <pb n="21" facs="tcp:3282:23"/> all puniſhments; but during the tyme of a ſoules ſtaying in
<hi>Purgatory,</hi> the want of the diuine viſion and ſight of God, is not properly to be accounted a puniſhment, or at leaſt not a puniſhment or payne more fearefull then thoſe puniſhments, which Martyrs haue ſuffered in this life; ſeeing that we, whiles we liue here vpon earth, do not ſee God, and yet we are nor ſaid truly to ſuffer <hi>poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam damni,</hi> any payne of loſſe; becauſe we ſhall ſee God in due tyme, if ſo we purge &amp; free our harts from ſin, as is our duty to doe.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3282:24"/> Yea the ancient holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Patriarchs, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, who remayning in <hi>Limbo Patrum,</hi> expecting the comming of the Sauiour of the world, did not as then ſee God; and yet they were not afflicted with any
<hi>poena damni,</hi> becauſe they were to ſee God in a prefixed &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned tyme. For thus A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> anſweres to the Rich glutton,
<hi>Luc.</hi> 16. <hi>Remember ſonne, that thou in thy lyfe tyme receiuedſt thy pleaſures, and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus paynes, now therefore he is comforted, and thou tormented.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In which words, we do not fynd, that Abraham ſaid;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3282:24"/> Lazarus was torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted with <hi>poena damni,</hi> with the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of loſſe; but that he was in ſolace &amp; comfort, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequently not in torment. And further, where <hi>S Simeon Luc.</hi> 2. ſayth: <hi>Nunc dimittis ſeruum tuum in pace &amp;c. Now</hi> (O Lord)
<hi>thou letteſt thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant depart in peace,</hi> was not of opinion, that through death he ſhould deſcend to any moſt inſupportable pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, but to a moſt ſweet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and peace.</p>
                  <p>To conclude <hi>S. Gregory l.</hi> 3. <hi>moral. c.</hi> 22. teacheth, that the ancient Patriarches and Fathers during their being in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3282:25"/> the place, called <hi>Limbus Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum,</hi> did not ſuffer there any torments, but did find reſt &amp; quietnes. The force of this obiection or argument is ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily diſſolued. The anſwere is this. Whiles we are li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing here vpon earth, we do not eaſily apprehend, how heauy a matter it is, to want the viſion and ſight of God; both in regard, that what things we apprehend by meanes of corporall phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſmes, and the miniſtery of the ſenſes, we do but obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely vnderſtand, as alſo, in that we being ſoftened and cheriſhed in corporall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3282:25"/> and pleaſures, we ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace and content our ſelues therewith, and thereupon we are not much ſollicitous and ſeeking after ſpirituall contentments.</p>
                  <p>The ancient Fathers and Prophets, were not tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with any
<hi>poena damni,</hi> payne of loſſe, in that they ſaw not God; becauſe they well did know, that this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craſtination &amp; deferring of enioying the viſion of God, was not occaſioned through any default in them, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the prefixed tyme of that moſt bleſſed ſight was not yet come.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:3282:26"/>But heere in our caſe, it falleth out otherwiſe, ſince touching thoſe ſoules, who are condemned, and relega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted (as it were) to <hi>Purgatory</hi> after the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of Chriſt, it is impoſſible, but that they ſhould be in the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree afflicted; for ſeeing they in that ſtate are depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued both of body, and of all corporall ſenſes, they cannot take further delight in ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible obiects, as in meate, drinke, riches, honours, in ſatisfying any carnall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp;c. but they who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly breath and thirſt after the contemplation of the firſt <pb n="27" facs="tcp:3282:26"/> Truth, and their enioying their <hi>Summum bonum,</hi> or <hi>chiefe good;</hi> for the obtayning whereof, as for their laſt end, they well know that they were created.</p>
                  <p>Heerunto may be adioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned this other reaſon; to wit, that the ſoules in <hi>Purgatory</hi> do wel know, that the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heauen is now made open to the faithfull Chriſtians, and that the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hindrance of not preſent enioying of it, is only the guilt of payne, contracted through their owne peculiar ſinnes; from whence it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but follow, that theſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:3282:27"/> ſoules are euen offended &amp; angry with themſelues, in that they alone are the cauſe of their long dilation &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring of their enioying ſo great an happines.</p>
                  <p>Theſe ſoules may well be reſembled to a man in great extremity of hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gar &amp; thirſt, though hauing a table before him furniſhed with all varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of meats, wynes &amp; choyce waters; and yet the only reaſon and impediment of his not feeding of them pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from ſome former miſcariage of the ſaid man, which hath deſeruedly cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed this his delay in taſting <pb n="29" facs="tcp:3282:27"/> of them.</p>
                  <p>We may add hereto, that the moſt ancient Fathers,
<hi>Austin, Gregory, Beda, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelme,</hi> and <hi>Bernard,</hi> do not ſpeake <hi>de poena damni,</hi> of the payne of loſſe, which payne all acknowledge to be moſt great; but <hi>de poena ignis,</hi> of the paine of fyer; &amp; this payne, they all with one conſent af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme to be more horrid &amp; intollerable, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts in this life. For althogh here vpon earth the torment by fyer is great, yet that fyer, which is not maintayned &amp; nouriſhed with wood or oyle, but is created as an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3282:28"/> of Gods iuſtice, to burne and torment ſoules, muſt without all doubt be moſt violent, and ſharpe in the higheſt degree,</p>
                  <p>Now, from the premiſſes it is euicted, that though we would not acknowledge <hi>poena damni,</hi> the temporary payne of loſſe, which is in <hi>Purgatory</hi> (to wit of the loſſe of the viſion of God for a long tyme) to be more inſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferable then all the torments in this life; yet that the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of the fyer in <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory</hi> is greater then any temporall afflictions in this lyfe, is euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly proued from
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:3282:28"/> the authorities of ſo many ancient Fathers aboue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced.</p>
                  <p>And becauſe, there are many men, who can hardly be induced to belieue any thing, which the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues haue not ſeene, God ſometimes therefore hath vouchſafed, to raiſe certaine perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s from death to lyfe; commanding them to relate to others li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, what themſelues tou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ching this payne haue ſeene.</p>
                  <p>Amonge ſo many eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witneſſes (as I may terme them) who haue ſeene the torments of <hi>Purgatory,</hi> I will alledge only two, the one be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing <pb n="32" facs="tcp:3282:29"/> a <hi>man,</hi> the other a <hi>woman,</hi> whoſe teſtimonies therein are to be accepted without any doubt or diffidency.</p>
                  <p>The one then, is <hi>Drithcl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> an Engliſh man; the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of which man <hi>Venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Bede</hi> writeth, &amp; relateth this accident, as a thing well knowne &amp; euident to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, it happening in
<hi>Bedes</hi> owne life tyme, with great amazement to all of thoſe dayes.</p>
                  <p>Thus then <hi>Bede</hi> writeth hereof in his fifth booke of the Hiſtory of the nation of England <hi>cap.</hi> 13. <hi>His tempori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus miraculum memorabile, &amp; <pb n="33" facs="tcp:3282:29"/> antiquorum ſimile in Britannia factum eſt &amp;c. In theſe tymes a most memorable miracle (and like to the ancient miracles) did fall out in Britanny. For to incite the liuing, touching care to be had concerning the death of the ſoule, a certaine Man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the tyme dead, was after reſtored to lyfe of Body, relating many things worthy of remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, of ſome of which I haue thought good at this preſent to make particular mention. It is this.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>There was a certaine Houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houlder, or Father of a family in the Country-Norman, belonging to the Humbri. This man did
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:3282:30"/> lead with his whole houſe a very religious lyfe. Who being taken with a ſudden infirmity and ſicknes in body, and his payne more, and more increaſing, he was brought to the howre of death, and dyed in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Night. But at the appearance of the morning he returned to life againe, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting himſelfe vp in bed, all thoſe, who accompanicd that night the dead Body, through feare and amazement preſently fled away.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But his wife, who loued him dearely (though fearing) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayned with him, whom he did comfort in theſe wordes: Feare
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:3282:30"/> not wife, for I am truly riſen from death; with which this night I haue beene houlden; and I am permitted to liue againe among men heere vpon earth; but not after the ſame manner as I was accustomed heretofore to liue, but after a far different ſort. Hereupon he preſently did ryſe out of his bed, and went to the Oratory, or Chappell belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to that village, ſpending the moſt part of the day in prayer. He inſtantly deuided all his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance into three partes; of the which one part he gaue to his wyfe, another to his children, and the third he distributed to the poore.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:3282:31"/>And, <hi>he with great ſpeed free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelfe from all care of the world, came to the Monastery called</hi> Mailros; <hi>and there ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Tonſure, the Abbot prouided for him a ſecret cell, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which he entred; and there continued till the day of his death, in ſuch great contrition of mind and body, that his very lyfe (though his tongue had beene ſilent) did ſpeake, that he had ſeene during the ſhort tyme he was afore dead, many things both fearefull, and to be deſired. For he deliuered the matter in this manner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lucidus erat aſpectu, &amp; cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus indumento, qui me ducebat <pb n="37" facs="tcp:3282:31"/> &amp;c. One of a lightſome counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and bright in apparell, did lead me. We came vnto a certaine valley of a great large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; profundity, but of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite length. That part of the valley, which was vpon our left hand, was most terrible through ſcorching flames; The other part thereof was no leſſe terrible through extremity of hayle, froſt, ſnow, and wynds. Both theſe wyde paſſages of this val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley were full of ſoules, of men and women, which ſeemed to be toſſed to and fro (as it were) through force and violence of boysterous stormes. For when they could not any longer endure <pb n="38" facs="tcp:3282:32"/> the violence of ſo great an heat, the poore miſerable ſoules did cast themſelues into the middest of that inſufferable cold, aboue related; and when as neither there they could fynd any rest, or eaſe, they then agayne leaped in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe inextinguiſhable flames of fyer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And whereas an infinite mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of poore ſoules I ſaw thus to be tormented with this vnfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate viciſsitude of torments, and without any intermiſsion or eaſe, I began to call to mynd, that perhaps this place was Hell, of the intollerable torments wherof I had before heard much ſpoken. My Conductour (who <pb n="39" facs="tcp:3282:32"/> went before me) anſwered to my preſent thought, ſaying; Do not ſo thinke, for this place, which thou ſeest, is not that Hell which thou ſuppoſest. Now the viſion of Hell, and after of Paradiſe, being explayned, which for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uity I omit; the Conductour thus further ſaid to the perſon rayſed from death: Scis omnia, quae vidisti? doſt thou know all theſe things, which thou hast ſeene? The raiſed party ſaid, No. I do not know them. To whom his Conductour thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed: That great vale, which thou haſt ſeene most dreadfull for flames of heate and fyer, as alſo for inſufferable cold, is
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:3282:33"/> that place, in which the ſoules of all thoſe are to be purged and chastized, who in their lyfe tyme delayed from time to time to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe their ſinnes, and to makc ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction for the wickednes by them perpetrated; and yet in the very laſt houre of their lyfe, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned true penitency and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition for their ſinnes, and ſo departed out of their bodies; which ſoules becauſe they made confeſsion of their ſinnes, and had penitency of them (though at the last houre of their death) do yet belong to the Kingdome of Heauen. And many of theſe poore ſoules are much eaſed by the prayers of the liuing, by Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes-deeds <pb n="41" facs="tcp:3282:33"/> of their friends, by their strict fastings, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially by the celebration of holy maſses in their behalfe; ſo as by theſe meanes diuers of them are freed from their torments be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the day of Iudgment.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Venerable Bede thus fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther addeth hereto; <hi>Cum ille incredibili auſteritate Corpus ſuum vexaret &amp;c. When as this man rayſed to life, did afflict his body with incredible austerity, praying, and prayſing God with hymns, he then standing in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter frozen through cold with yce, his fellow Monkes would ſay to him; It is wonderfull, ô Brother Drithelmus, that thou <pb n="42" facs="tcp:3282:34"/> art able to endure ſuch aſperity of cold; He then replyed, Frigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diora vidi, I haue ſeene much more cold places. And when they in lyke ſort ſaid to him; mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, quod tam auſteram tenere continentiam velis &amp;c. It is wonderfull, that thou wilt keep this austere co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinency in meates &amp;c. He anſwered: Auſteriora vidi, I haue ſeene greater auste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. And in this ſort, through an indefatigable deſire of the ioyes of Heauen he tamed and ſubdued his old feeble body vntill the day of his death, he much profiting many by his perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and conuerſation of lyfe.</hi> Thus far <hi>S. Bede</hi> in his rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:3282:34"/> of this hiſtory.</p>
                  <p>Now, that the contents hereof are moſt true, I little doubt, becauſe it is agreable to the ſacred Scripture, in the booke of Iob
<hi>cap.</hi> 24 <hi>Ad nimium calorem, tranſeunt ab aquis niuium: from waters of ſnow, they paſse to ouermuch heate.</hi> Againe <hi>S. Bede</hi> (a Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable &amp; moſt godly man) recordeth the ſame, as hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening out in his owne dayes and lifetime. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, there did follow out of this viſion great ſpirituall benefit, the which God is accuſtomed to draw and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract out of ſuch miraculous <pb n="44" facs="tcp:3282:35"/> euents, and not curioſity or vanity, but the health of many ſoules by their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion to pennance &amp; ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. In this next place will I come to the teſtimony of a moſt admirable woman, her name was <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> whoſe life is written by <hi>Thomas Cantipratenſis</hi> of the order of <hi>S. Dominicke,</hi> a man moſt worthy of credit, and who liued in the dayes of the ſaid <hi>Christina.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſame is in like ſort witneſſed by that Venerable man <hi>Iacobus de Vitriaco (l. de vita &amp; rebus gestis B. Mariae de Oegnies)</hi> a pious and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <pb n="45" facs="tcp:3282:35"/> Cardinall, who in a booke of his maketh men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of diuers holy women, and particularly of this
<hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stina Mirabilis,</hi> whoſe life he relateth moſt briefly in a ſhort <hi>Compendium.</hi> Now this Virgin <hi>Chriſtina</hi> doth thus ſpeake of her ſelfe, inſtantly after ſhe did riſe from death to lyfe in the ſight of many then liuing: <hi>Statim vt è corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re exceſsi, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Preſently after I did leaue my body, certaine Angels of God, being ministers of the light, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued my ſoule, and brought it to an obſcure, darke, and horrid place, being full and repleniſhed
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:3282:36"/> with the ſoules of men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. The torments, which I did behould in that place, were ſo extreme, violent, and inſuffera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as that they cannot be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, in any words. I did ſee there diuers, with whom I was acquainted, whiles they here li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vpon the earth. I did much pitty thoſe poore miſerable ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les. I demaunded of my Condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours, what place this was, for I did imagine that it was Hell. They anſwered, that it was the place of Purgatory, reſerued for ſuch ſinners, who had obtayned true penitency of their ſinnes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their death, but had not yet performed any actuall ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction <pb n="47" facs="tcp:3282:36"/> for their Crimes in their lyfe tyme committed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>After this, my Conductours brought me to behould the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment of the damned in Hel, where alſo I did find certaine perſons knowne to me in their lyfe tyme. After this I was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted vp to Paradiſe, euen to the Throne of the diuine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesty, where I did behould our Lord wellcomming me. I reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced exceſsiuely thereat, as being then perſwaded, that I should there remayne with our Lord for all eternity. But he preſently anſwered me, ſaying: Most well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come daughter, thou shalt with out all doubt finally ſtay with <pb n="48" facs="tcp:3282:37"/> me, but here I put to thee an ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, of which of theſe two things thou hadst rather make choyce, to wit, whether thou had<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest rather now ſtay with me for all eternity, or els to returne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world and earth againe, and there reſuming thy former body to ſuffer paynes, though without any danger to thy body, by which paynes thou mayest free &amp; ſet at liberty thoſe ſoules, which thou behoulding in Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, didst commiſerate &amp; pitty, that ſo by this means, men and women yet liuing vpon the earth, through the example of thy penitent lyfe, abstayning from commiting more facino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <pb n="49" facs="tcp:3282:37"/> Crymes, and performing in ſatisfaction of them, what they ought to do, may in the end (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing enriched with store of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits and good deeds) be conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Now I, without any pauſe or delay anſwered, that I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther returne to my body vnder the former condition propoſed to me; and thereupon our Lord taking it well, that I shewed my ſelfe ſo ready in the choyce, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth my ſoule to be restored to its body. In the performance whereof it was wonderfull to behould the incredible ſwiftnes, and celerity of the bleſſed ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits. For euen in that very <pb n="50" facs="tcp:3282:38"/> houre, when it is ſayd in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of the Maſſe, (which was then offered for me) Agnus Dei, O Lambe of God &amp;c. my ſoule was placed before the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Maieſty, and at the third time of the ſaying of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid words, Agnus, Dei; the Angells restored me to my body. And thus the matter ſtandeth touching my departure out of this world, and my after returne to lyfe; ſince all this was done concerning my being restored to lyfe, for the chastizing of men, and their amendment in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and conuerſation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Therefore I would intreate all perſons, that they would not <pb n="51" facs="tcp:3282:38"/> be troubled, or affrighted with ſuch things, as they shall ſee in me. The things do exceed mans vnderſtanding, which (God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding) shalbe performed in me. Neither haue ſuch euents at any tyme hapned among mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall men.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus much did ſhe ſpeake. And then the wryter of her lyfe adioyneth theſe words following, concerning her <hi>Cap.</hi> 6. <hi>Tum vero caepit illa exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere &amp;c. Thtn she did begin to exerciſe and put in practiſe ſuch ſeuerities, for the performa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of which she was ſent by our Lord: She did voluntarily enter into burning Ouens, &amp; was tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:3282:39"/> in thoſe fyers; ſo as through the straytnes of the place and paynes, she made a fearefull &amp; horrible noyſe; But after she came out of thoſe places, there was not to be ſeene in her body any print, or marke of ſuch her burnings.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And then the foreſaid Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour thus further procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in his diſcourſe <hi>Cap.</hi> 7. <hi>Sub aquis</hi> Moſae <hi>fluminis hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berno tempore, cum rigerent om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia gelu &amp;c. She very often &amp; long stood in the waters of the riuer</hi> Moſa, <hi>in winter time, when it was congealed with frost, remayning there in ſuch manner ſix dayes, and more.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:3282:39"/>And then a little after the foreſaid Authour thus fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſayth, <hi>cap.</hi> 9. <hi>Interdum in aquis orans &amp;c. She ſometymes praying in the waters, was ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed by them vpon the wheele of a water mill, and ſo in most hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible manner was borne about with the wheele thereof, being notwithstanding perfect &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hurt in all the parts of her body.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And the Authour thus more writeth, <hi>ibid. Surgebat quandoque medijs noctibus, &amp; totius Oppidi Trudonenſis canes in ſe concitans &amp;c. She often tymes ryſing about midnight, would stir vp against her all the dogs of the towne of S. Truyen, <pb n="54" facs="tcp:3282:40"/> she ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning before them following her, like a ſwyft Deare, throgh certaine obſcure places full of bryars and thornes, in ſo much, as she was pricked &amp; her skinne torne in diuers places, as that no part of her body was free from wounds; and yet after her ſhee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of much bloud thereby, no prints, ſcarrs, or marks of any wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds or pricks were to be ſeene in her body.</hi> Thus far the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Authour.</p>
                  <p>Now, that this his Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all ſet downe, was moſt true, appeareth ſeuerall wayes; Firſt, becauſe, as I ſaid aboue, he had
<hi>Iacobus</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop and Cardinall of <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triacum,</hi>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:3282:40"/> (a moſt graue man) to beare witneſſe thereof. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly, in that the authour of this Hiſtory did relate paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages done in his owne life tyme, and in the ſame Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince, wherein himſelfe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, ſeeing he was Biſhop, and ſuffragan to the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of
<hi>Cambray.</hi> Thirdly, in that the matter and Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it ſelfe euen publikely (as it were) depoſeth and auer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the truth hereof; to wit, that her body was ſo after conformed and ſtrengthned by diuine power, as that it ſhould ſuffer payne by fyer, and yet ſhould not be diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued;
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:3282:41"/> ſhould receaue wounds and ſheed much bloud, and yet no prints of thoſe wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds ſhould appeare.</p>
                  <p>In this ſort this moſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed woman liued, not for the ſpace of few dayes only, but during all the time of fourty two yeares, after her returne to lyfe. And laſtly; becauſe by this courſe of her life ſhe conuerted many to true pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and compunction of their ſinnes, and after her death was glorious and emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent for miracles: therefore <hi>God</hi> by ſuch examples aboue inſiſted vpon, would ſtop the mouths of ſuch incredulous <pb n="57" facs="tcp:3282:41"/> perſons, who are not afraid ſometymes to demand, <hi>Who hath returned from Hell? who hath ſeene the torments either of Hell, or Purgatory?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Behould heere, we haue two faythfull Witneſſes, a
<hi>man</hi> and a <hi>woman,</hi> who haue ſeene the moſt bitter and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable torments of <hi>Hell,</hi> and <hi>Purgatory;</hi> and therefore ſuch men do wholy reſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excuſable, who do not bleeue theſe points: and yet thoſe men are more inexcuſable, who belieuing theſe &amp; ſuch like examples, do not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding neglect, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne them, forbearing to <pb n="58" facs="tcp:3282:42"/> make ſatisfaction for their ſinnes to God, in faſting, mourning, and bewayling the moſt poore ſtate of their ſoules. But let vs come to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther heads aboue ſpecifyed.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond Head was, <hi>the long and dayly ſufferance of the paynes of Purgatory.</hi> I grant, that there is a wryter (other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe of a great name and worth) who did maintayne, that not any ſoule remayned tormented in <hi>Purgatory</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue twenty yeares, yea per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps not aboue ten yeares; notwithſtanding the vſe of the Catholike Church tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth the contrary, which <pb n="59" facs="tcp:3282:42"/> preſcribeth Anniuerſary Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices of the Holy maſſe to be offered vp for ſoules de parted, not only for ten yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, but euen for a hundred yeares, and more.</p>
                  <p>This point appeareth fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the viſion, which we related aboue out of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable Bede,</hi> which ſheweth that many Soules are to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne to be tormented in <hi>Purgatory,</hi> euen till the day of Iudgment And the ſame ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity may receaue its further warrant from the authority of <hi>Tertullian,</hi> a moſt ancient Authour, who ſpeaking of
<hi>Purgatory</hi> vnder the name of <pb n="60" facs="tcp:3282:43"/> Hell, thus writeth,
<hi>l. de Ani<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ma cap.</hi> 17. <hi>In carcerem te man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det Infernum &amp;c. Hell may ſend thee to that priſon, from whence, vntill thy ſinnes be expiated, thou shalt not depart, perhaps till the day of thy reſurrection.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But <hi>S. Cyprian Epist.</hi> 2. <hi>l.</hi> 4. diſcourſeth of this point more perſpicuouſly &amp; plain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, thus ſaying: <hi>Aliud est pro peccatis longo tempore crucia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum purgari igne &amp;c. It is one thing to be tormented with fyer for ones ſinnes, during a long tyme; and other thing, to haue purged his ſinnes through a mans owne ſufferance and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerity of lyfe.</hi> Which point <pb n="61" facs="tcp:3282:43"/> receaueth its further proofe from the viſion of bleſſed
<hi>Ludgardis,</hi> a moſt holy and eminent Virgin, whoſe lyfe was written by <hi>Thomas Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipratenſis</hi> aboue mentioned, who had written the lyfe of <hi>Chriſtina Mirabilis.</hi> And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the matter is of Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, &amp; concerneth much (by way of example) the Prelats of the Church, I will here ſet downe the words of the Authour himſelfe, which are to be found in the ſecond booke of the lyfe of holy <hi>Ludgardis (apud Surium tom</hi> 3. 16. <hi>Iunij.)</hi> The words are theſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:3282:44"/>
                     <hi>Hoc ferè tempore Dominus Innocentius Papa tertius &amp;c. About this tyme Innocentius the third, being Pope, after the Councell of Lateran was cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated, departed this lyfe, and did preſently after appeare vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly to Ludgardis. After ſhe ſaw him compaſſed about on all ſydes with a great fyre, she asked him, who he was. He anſwered, that he was Innocentius the Pope. But ſhe replying with griefe ſaid, What, is the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Father of vs all, thus tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented for ſo long a tyme? He anſwered, I am in theſe flames for three cauſes. Which Crymes of myne had iustly deſerued, <pb n="63" facs="tcp:3282:44"/> that I had beene puniſhed with eternity of torments; but that through the interceſsion of the most holy Mother of God, (to whom I did build &amp; conſecrate a Monaſtery) I had repentance of my ſaid ſinnes. And ſo it is, that I haue eſcaped eternall dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; Neuertheleſse I shalbe tormented with most cruell pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, euen till the day of Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. That I am permitted to appeare to thee, thereby to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate thee to procure prayers &amp; ſuffrages to be ſaid for me; this fauour the mother of mercy ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned of her ſonne in my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe. And at the ſpeaking of theſe least words, he instantly
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:3282:45"/> vaniſhed away. Ludgardis did make knowne this his neceſsity to her ſiſters, that he might be holpen with their prayers. But Ludgardis herſelfe taking great commiſeration of his poore state, did vndergoe wonderfull auste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities for his reliefe. Let the Reader take notice, that Lud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardis did acquaint vs with thoſe cauſes of this mans tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which we for the reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of ſo great a Pope, haue thought good to conceale.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus much the former Authour, touching the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of
<hi>Ludgardis,</hi> which example hath often affected me with great feare and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour. <pb n="65" facs="tcp:3282:45"/> For if ſo laudable a Pope, who in the eies of men appeared not only good, but alſo holy, and worthy imitation, was in great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of being eternally dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in Hell; yet in lieu ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is to be puniſhed with moſt inſufferable flames, euen vntill the day of iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; what Prelat may not feare? Who ought not to ſearch moſt narrowly, into euery corner of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience? For I am perſuaded that ſo great a Pope did not commit any mortall ſinnes, except he committing them vnder the ſhew of ſome <pb n="66" facs="tcp:3282:46"/> good, was therein deceaued by his flatterers, &amp; ſuch his Domeſticks, of whom it is ſayd in the Ghoſpell,
<hi>Matth.</hi> 10. <hi>Inimici hominis domestici eius: A mans enemyes shalbe they of his owne houſehould.</hi> Therefore as being taught by this great example, let vs all labour to make moſt dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent inquiry into our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, for feare they be not erroneous, though to our ſelues they appeare right and ſincere.</p>
                  <p>But let vs returne vnto that point, from which we haue digreſſed. It is not to be doubted, but that the <pb n="67" facs="tcp:3282:46"/> paynes of Purgatory may be extended to ten, twenty, a hundred, yea to a thouſand yeares. But let vs grant for the tyme, that thoſe paynes ſhould endure but ten, or twenty yeares; who is able to endure moſt dreadfull &amp; inexplicable torments for the ſpace of twenty yeares without any intermiſſion or eaſe? Now, that thoſe bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings are to be without any alleuiation or reſt, appeareth from the viſion, which we haue aboue related, out of <hi>Venerable Bede.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Certainly, if a man were aſſured, that he ſhould conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue <pb n="68" facs="tcp:3282:47"/> afflicted for the ſpace of twenty yeares, without any intermiſſion or relaxation, with the paine of the Goute, or of the ſtomacke, or the Head-ach, or tooth-ach, or of the Stone; &amp; that he could not by reaſon of ſuch his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, take any ſleep or reſt; no doubt ſuch a man had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther make choyce to dye, then to perſeuer, and liue in this miſerable caſe. And if choyce were giuen him, whether he would remayne for twenty yeares without any reſpiration and eaſe in thoſe foreſaid paynes, or would ſuffer loſſe of all his <pb n="69" facs="tcp:3282:47"/> ſtate and goods; Certainly he would with a moſt ready mind, ſeeke to be depriued of all his temporall meanes, that ſo thereby, he might free himſelfe from ſo conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall &amp; cruell paynes: with how much more reaſon then, ought euery wiſe man to make choyce of vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going of Penance, accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with its fruits, which fruits are, watching, Prayer, Faſting, Almes deeds, and eſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pecially teares, which are a ſigne of true Penance?</p>
                  <p>Now if we add to the acer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bity of theſe paynes and the long continuance of them, <pb n="70" facs="tcp:3282:48"/> this third Calamity; to wit, <hi>that the ſoules in Purgatory can in no ſort help themſelues,</hi> their infelicity &amp; miſery is much increaſed therby. For here among men conuerſing on earth, there is hardly to be found any one ſo depreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in miſery and calamity, but that either by flight, or by reſiſtance, or by media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of friends, or by appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to another Iudge, or by humbly beſeeching the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Iudge, or by ſome other meanes, he may free himſelfe in ſome meaſure from the vexations, with which he is enuironed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:3282:48"/>But (alas) in <hi>Purgatory</hi> the Soules can do nothing, but only patiently ſuffer their puniſhment. True it is, that Holy Men liuing heere on earth, may pray for the dead, may offer vp almes, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſatisfactory workes for the ſoules in <hi>Purgatory.</hi> But this priuiledge is not gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the ſoules themſelues being in
<hi>Purgatory,</hi> except by a certaine Priuiledge to ſome few, and this moſt rare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; to wit, to appeare to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing men, and to beſeech ayde and help by their cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. Therefore the ſtate and condition of thoſe ſoules are <pb n="72" facs="tcp:3282:49"/> moſt miſerable, who being in thoſe torments, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get any eaſe or help to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, or to the ſoules of their Father, Sonne, Brother, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſiſter or wyfe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or of any other friend lying in <hi>Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But perhaps, It may be here ſuggeſted, that few are thoſe Soules who come to <hi>Purgatory,</hi> and therefore the puniſhments there inflicted, are not much to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, but in a ſort to be ſleighted, and ſmally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded. But to this I anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>were, <hi>that the ſoules which lye cruciated &amp; tormented in Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, <pb n="73" facs="tcp:3282:49"/> are innumerable; and ſo many, as that the number of them is ſufficient to moue and stir vp mercy, though their tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were far more eaſy and light.</hi> This is euident, ſeeing we are inſtructed a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore from the hiſtory of Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable <hi>Bede,</hi> that
<hi>Drithelmus</hi> did ſee an infinite number of ſoules in
<hi>Purgatory,</hi> as alſo fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lyfe of Bleſſed
<hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtina,</hi> that the place of <hi>Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory</hi> was a moſt vaſt &amp; huge place, repleniſhed, &amp; filled with ſoules.</p>
                  <p>Neither can it be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, ſeeing nothing that is defiled, and contaminated, <pb n="74" facs="tcp:3282:50"/> can enter into the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heauen, but they only, are able to penetrate vnto the ſight of God, (which is a light, and in whom, there is not any dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenes) and to that place of infinite purity who are tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly holy and immaculate, &amp; are me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of that Church, in which there is not either <hi>macula,</hi> or <hi>ruga,</hi> ſpot, or wrincle, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. Now, who theſe men are, are moſt rare and moſt few; and therfore it followeth, that all others, who belong to the number of the Elect, are to paſſe through the torments and
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:3282:50"/> paynes of <hi>Purgatory.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now, from all the former paſſages of this diſcourſe, it may neceſſarily be gathered, that the <hi>Doue</hi> hath iuſt cauſe daily to lament and mourne for ſo many me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of hers, which with an infinite de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire thirſt after their heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Country; and yet are in the meane time detayned from thence by intollerable flames of fyer, and are cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciated &amp; afflicted with moſt bitter &amp; inexplicable paines.</p>
                  <p>Thus far doth the Godly <hi>Cardinall Bellarmyne</hi> diſcourſe of theſe former foure Heads, touching the Nature of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:3282:51"/> Which diſcourſe (in regard both of his Learning &amp; Sanctity) ought to ſway and preuayle much with all ſuch good &amp; pious Engliſh Catholikes, who are ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, and carefull of their owne ſoules good. Now the Authour of this Treatiſe wil conclude this <hi>first Section,</hi> by adioyning a Reaſon drawne from <hi>Schoole Diuinity,</hi> which demonſtrateth that the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of <hi>Purgatory are far more atrocious and intollerable, then any paynes or torments of this life can be.</hi> It is this.</p>
                  <p>Three things do concurre as well to griefe or payne, as
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:3282:51"/> to ioy. To wit; <hi>Potentia, Obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum, &amp; Coniunctio vnius cum altero</hi> (as <hi>S. Tho. p.</hi> 2. <hi>q.</hi> 31. <hi>ar.</hi>
5. ſaith:) An intelligent, or at leaſt a ſentient <hi>Power,</hi> or
<hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty;</hi> a conuenient <hi>Obiect</hi> to that <hi>Power;</hi> and an
<hi>Vnion</hi> or Coniunction of the <hi>Obiect</hi> with the <hi>Power.</hi> Now as con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Power,</hi> doubtleſly <hi>Potentia rationalis,</hi> a Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Power</hi> or Faculty, is more capable of payne or griefe, then <hi>Potentia animalis,</hi> a ſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſible Faculty, or Function; For if we reſpect <hi>Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> or knowing, the
<hi>Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding</hi> in a <hi>Rationall ſoule, is</hi> (as it were) a mayne Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine; <pb n="78" facs="tcp:3282:52"/> the <hi>Senſe</hi> but a ſmall Riuer. So far as concerneth the <hi>Appetite</hi> or <hi>Deſire,</hi> the wil of a <hi>Rationall Soule</hi> is a maine Fountayne alſo; The
<hi>Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite,</hi> (being inferiour to it) is but like a ſmall Riuer. See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therfore the naked ſoule it ſelfe, is immediatly tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, the griefe thereof ought to be the greateſt, in reſpect of the Patient; for here in this lyfe not ſo much the ſoule, as the body is tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented; &amp; by reaſon of the paynes of the body, ſome griefe and dolour paſſeth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſoule.</p>
                  <p>Now concerning the <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect;</hi> 
                     <pb n="79" facs="tcp:3282:52"/> The fyer of <hi>Purgatory</hi> muſt be far more violent, horrible, &amp; intenſe, then the fyer in this world is; ſeeing that fyer is created, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted, as an inſtrument of Gods Iuſtice, who would ſhew his power in the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, touching the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction of the Power with the Obiect;</hi> the Coniunction of the Soule with the fyer in <hi>Purgatory</hi> ſhall be moſt ſtrait and (as it were) intrinſecall. For heere in this world, where all things are corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and bodily, there is no Coniunction made, but only <pb n="80" facs="tcp:3282:53"/> by the touch of the Extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, or vtmoſt parts of the bodyes, and the <hi>Superficies</hi> of things; wheras in
<hi>Purgatory,</hi> the torments and fyer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, ſhall penetrate moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly the very ſoule it ſelfe. Thus farre, touching this firſt
<hi>Section.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of the meanes to auoyde, at least to mitigate, the paynes of Purgatory.</hi> SECT. II.</head>
               <p>HAuing in the precedent <hi>Section,</hi> ſhewed out of the iudgment of the moſt <pb n="81" facs="tcp:3282:53"/> learned <hi>Cardinall Bellarmyne,</hi> the atrocity of the paynes of <hi>Purgatory,</hi> and ſome other Circumſtances acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paning the ſaid paynes; in this next place it is conuenient to ſet downe the meanes, through force whereof the ſayd pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes may receaue ſome alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiation and mitigation: I imitating herein the Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian, who firſt inquireth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the diſeaſe, &amp; after preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribeth Medicines, for the curing of the ſame.</p>
               <p>Theſe meanes (according to the Doctrine of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church) are theſe following: To wit, <hi>the most <pb n="82" facs="tcp:3282:54"/> holy Sacrifice of the Maſse, Prayer, &amp; Almes-deeds, or good workes;</hi> according to thoſe words of <hi>S. Austin (ſerm.</hi> 32. <hi>deverb. Apoſt.) Orationibus ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctae Eccleſiae, &amp; ſacrificio ſaluta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri, &amp; Eleemoſynis non est du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bium mortuos adiuuari; It is not to be doubted, but that the Soules of the dead are helped by prayers of the holy Church, by the healthfull Sacrifice, and by Almes deeds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>With whom accordeth <hi>S. Chryſoſtome (Hom.</hi> 41.
<hi>in</hi> 1. <hi>ad Cor.)</hi> ſaying; <hi>Iuuatur mortuus non lachrymis, ſed precibus, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicationibus, Eleemoſynis. A dead man is helped, not with <pb n="83" facs="tcp:3282:54"/> teares, but with prayers, ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, and Almes-deeds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>With which two former Fathers, Venerable <hi>Bede</hi> (to omit many other to auoyde prolixity) doth conſpire in theſe words. <hi>(l.</hi>
5. <hi>hiſt. c.</hi> 13.) <hi>Multos, preces viuentium, &amp; Eleemoſynae &amp;c. The prayers of the liuing, Alms-deeds, Fasting, and principally the Celebration of the Maſſe do helpe many who are dead, that they may be freed from their torments, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the day of Iudgment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But of theſe three ſeuerall kinds of <hi>Suffrages</hi> for reliefe of the ſoules in <hi>Purgatory,</hi> I will chiefly inſiſt in ſhewing <pb n="84" facs="tcp:3282:55"/> the force and efficacy of <hi>good works,</hi> or <hi>Almes-deeds.</hi> In the explication of which point I will firſt reſt in the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the <hi>Sacred Scriptures;</hi> Secondly in the iudgment of the <hi>ancient Fathers.</hi> And Firſt, touching the ſacred Scriptures, I will alledge di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers paſſages thereof, which although they proue imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly the great vertue of <hi>Good works,</hi> and
<hi>Almes-deeds,</hi> for the gayning of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, and remitting of the puniſhment of eter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nall Damnation; yet (as the <hi>Logitians</hi> phraſe is,) <hi>à for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiori,</hi> they much more proue,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:3282:55"/> that the Temporary puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of <hi>Purgatory,</hi> may be taken away, and (as it were) bought out by the pryce of them.</p>
               <p>Now, to begin with the teſtimonies of Gods Holy writ, we firſt read thus ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: <hi>Eleemoſyna ab omni pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to &amp; à morte liberat, &amp; non pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titur animam ire in tenebras. Tob.</hi> 4.
<hi>Almes-deeds free a man from ſinne and death, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer not the ſoule to deſcend into darknes.</hi> And in another place we read: <hi>Sicut aqua extinguit ignem, ita Eleemoſyna extin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>guit peccatum. Eccl.</hi> 3 <hi>As water doth extinguiſh the fyer, ſo do <pb n="86" facs="tcp:3282:56"/> Almes-deeds extinguiſh ſinne.</hi> Yea <hi>Almes deeds,</hi> and <hi>Good workes</hi> are ſo powerfull, as that our <hi>Sauiour</hi> after he had charged the Phariſyes with diuers great ſinnes, yet thus concludeth, <hi>Luc.</hi> 11.
<hi>Verum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamen date Eleemoſynas, &amp; ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce omnia munda ſunt vobis; but notwithstanding, do you giue Almes, and behould all things are cleane vnto you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And which is more, Gods holy word exte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of
<hi>Almes-deeds</hi> euen to the Gentills and Heathens, for thus we fynd it ſaid to <hi>Nabuchodonoſor,</hi> who was a Pagan: <hi>Heare my Counſell</hi> (O <pb n="87" facs="tcp:3282:56"/> King) <hi>and redeeme thy ſinnes with Almes, and thy Iniquities with works of Mercy. Dan</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>Now, if <hi>Good works</hi> of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and
<hi>Almes-deeds,</hi> perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med euen by Heathens and wicked liuers, be ſo much reſpected by God; much more then, <hi>Good workes</hi> of Chriſtians and good liuers, are accepted of God, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the preuenting the paynes of eternall damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but alſo (which is leſſe) of the temporall paynes of <hi>Purgatory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To come to the ancient Fathers: <hi>S. Cyprian</hi> calleth
<hi>Eleemoſyna, Solatium grande <pb n="88" facs="tcp:3282:57"/> credentium, ſecuritatis noſtrae ſalutare praeſidium: Almes-deeds a great ſolace of the faithfull, a healthfull ſafegard of our ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity.</hi> Againe the ſaid Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>ſerm. de Eleemoſ. Sicut lauacro aquae ſalutaris Gehennae ignis extinguitur, ita Eleemoſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis &amp; precibus nostris delictoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> flamma ſopitur; As the fyer of Hell is extinguiſhed through our waſhing in that healthfull water</hi> (meaning at the tyme of our
<hi>Baptiſme) ſo the flame of our ſinnes, is abated by our good workes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To whoſe iudgment <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> alludeth in theſe words. <hi>ſerm.</hi> 31. <hi>Eleemoſyna <pb n="89" facs="tcp:3282:57"/> quodammodo animarum aliud est lauacrum &amp;c. Lauacrum ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel datur, &amp; ſemel veniam pol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>licetur; Eleemoſynam autem quoties feceris, toties veniam promereris. Almes-deedes is a certayne kind of Baptiſme &amp;c.</hi> But
<hi>Baptiſme</hi> (meaning the Sacrament of <hi>Baptiſme) is but once administred, and but once it promiſeth forgiuenes of ſinnes; But as often, as thou shalt do ſome act of Almes-deeds, ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten doſt thou procure forgiuenes of ſinnes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S. Chryſostome</hi> thus auer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, <hi>Hom.</hi> 25.
<hi>in act. Apost. Non est peccatum, quod non poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit purgare Eleemoſyna. There <pb n="90" facs="tcp:3282:58"/> is no ſinne ſo great which Almes-deed cannot purge, and take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</hi> And more: <hi>Omne peccatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> infra illam stat: All ſinne is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Almes deeds;</hi> meaning that <hi>Almes-deeds,</hi> and
<hi>Good Workes</hi> can extinguiſh the greateſt ſinne.</p>
               <p>To conclude, <hi>S. Leo</hi> thus writeth of this point,
<hi>ſerm.</hi> 5. <hi>de Collectis: Eleemoſynae pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata delent, mortem perimunt, &amp; poenam perpetui ignis extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunt. Almes-deeds do blot out ſin, destroy death, and extinguiſh the payne of perpetuall fyer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus we ſee, what won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull efficacy and vertue both the Holy <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and <pb n="91" facs="tcp:3282:58"/> the <hi>Ancient Father</hi> aſcribe &amp; attribute to workes of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and <hi>Almes-deeds;</hi> from whence we may infallibly conclude; that ſince ſuch <hi>good-works</hi> are of force to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh the eternity of Hell fyer, much more the tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary flames of <hi>Purgatory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Heere now I hould it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient to anſwere two Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iections, which ſuch men who are in ſlauery to their riches, not hauing the mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimity and reſolution to part with their ſiluer to any good and charitable vſes, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for their owne ſoules good, or for the benefit of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <pb n="88" facs="tcp:3282:59"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:3282:59"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:3282:60"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:3282:60"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:3282:61"/> that are needfull, are accuſtomed to inſiſt vpon. The firſt is, (ſay ſuch men) <hi>My goods are my owne, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I am not obliged to giue any part of them, but to what end my ſelfe best pleaſeth.</hi> Their ſecond argument and more potent is, <hi>I haue wyfe and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, I am bound by the Law of God to prouide for them, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter my prouiſion for them, I ſhall haue nothing remayning to bestow vpon good and charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the firſt of theſe two Obiections I anſwere; Firſt, if we ſhould dreame for the tyme that a mans temporall <pb n="93" facs="tcp:3282:61"/> goods were abſolutely at his owne diſpoſall, &amp; that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it were in his power, whether he would giue any part thereof to good vſes or no: to this I firſt ſay, that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting for the preſent, that a man had ſole dominion ouer his owne goods, and might diſpoſe of them, as beſt pleaſeth himſelfe; yet certaine it is from the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer authorities, both ſacred and humane, that, that man who is ſo wholy drowned in his temporall ſtate, as that he cannot endure to part with ſome reaſonable ſhare of them to pious vſes, ſhall <pb n="94" facs="tcp:3282:62"/> hardly enioy Heauen (for without Charity a man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaued) much leſſe, ſhall he neuer eſcape the pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of <hi>Purgatory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, I affirme, that it is a falſe ground to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that a man is ſo ſole a <hi>Proprietary</hi> of the goods he poſſeſſeth, as that he may, as his owne paſſion and appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite carryeth him, diſpoſe of them without giuing any part therof to needfull and charitable vſes. And that this is moſt true, I produce in proofe thereof the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and words of theſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend <hi>Fathers</hi> following.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:3282:62"/>To begin with <hi>S. Bernard,</hi> who thus ſpeaketh to rich Men, in the perſon of the poore <hi>(in Ep. ad Epiſc. Seno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſem) Nostrum eſt pauperes clamant &amp;c. The poore crye out, It is ours, which you wastfully ſpend; That is taken from vs most cruelly, which you (rich men) wast vaynely.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S. Gregory</hi> writeth in this ſort (<hi>in</hi> 3.
<hi>parte Pastor curae admonit.</hi> 22.) <hi>Admonendi ſunt &amp;c. Men are to be admoniſhed, and instructed, that the earth, of which we all are, is common to all men; and that therefore it affoardeth nouriſhment to all men: in regard wherof they but <pb n="96" facs="tcp:3282:63"/> invayne and without cauſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute themſelues to be innocent herein, who peculiarly challenge to themſelues, the common guift and liberality of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S. Auſtin (Tract. in Pſal.</hi> 147.) <hi>Superflua diuiti, neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria ſunt pauperi; res alienae poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidentur, cùm ſuperflua poſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentur. Thoſe goods, which are but ſuperfluous to euery rich man, neceſſarily belong to the poore; Another mans ſubſtance is poſseſſed, when ſuperfluous ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches are poſſeſſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S. Chryſostome (Hom.</hi> 34. <hi>ad populum Antioch.) Non ad hoc accepiſti &amp;c. Thou haſt not receaued thy riches, to conſume
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:3282:63"/> them in wastfull expences, but that thou ſhouldst beſtow much of them in Almes-deeds.</hi> And againe in the ſame place:
<hi>Tuarum rerum &amp;c. O man, thou art but a diſpenſer or steward of thy owne ſubſtance; no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe, then he, who diſpenſeth and distributeth the goods of the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S Ierome (vide Gratian. diſt.</hi> 42. <hi>Can Hoſpitale:) Aliena rapere conuincitur, qui vltra ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi neceſſaria retinere probatur? He is conuinced to take euen by violence, thoſe riches which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to others, who is iuſtly accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to retayne to himſelfe more, then is neceſſary to his state.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:3282:64"/>
                  <hi>S. Baſill (in orat. in illud, Destruam horrea mea:) At tu nonne ſpoliator es, qui quae diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſanda accepisti, propria re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putas? Art not thou euen a Robber, who takest thoſe things &amp; that ſubstance for thy owne, which thou hast receaued to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stribute to others? The bread which thou haſt in thy houſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to the Hungry man, the Coate to the Naked man &amp;c. Quocirca tot pauperibus iniu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riam facis, quot dare valeres: Wherefore, thou dost iniure ſo many poore men, how many thou art able to relieue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For greater breuity I will conclude with <hi>S. Ambroſe,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:3282:64"/> ſerm.</hi> 81. <hi>Sed ais, quid iniustum est, ſi cùm aliena non inuadam, propria diligenter ſeruem? O impudens dictum! Propria dicis? Quae? And then after: Non mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus est criminis, quàm habenti tollere, cùm poſsis &amp; abundes, indigentibus denegare. But thou wilt ſay? What iniustice is it in me, if ſo I do not inuade other mens ſubstance, but reſerue my owne proper riches only to my ſelfe? O impudent and ſhameleſse ſaying! Callest thou them thy proper riches? Which be they? It is no leſſe a cryme, to deny to giue to the poore, when thou art able to giue, and doſt abound; then to take riches from thoſe,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:3282:65"/> who already do enioy them.</hi> Thus far touching the
<hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> Iudgment in this point, wherewith to ſhut vp the mouths of worldly and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous men.</p>
               <p>Now, for the better vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the former Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities, we are to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceaue, that thoſe who poſſeſſe ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, be indeed true Lords ouer them, if ſo they be iuſtly obtayned and gotten: if the Compariſon be heere made in reſpect of other men; yet with reference to God, they are not to be accounted Lords, or abſolute <hi>Proprieta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes,</hi> but only <hi>diſpenſers</hi> of <pb n="101" facs="tcp:3282:65"/> them. For God created all things, and ordayned, that ſome men are rich, others poore; yet not in that ſort, as ſome ſhould be ſo rich, as that they ſhall abound with all ſuperfluities; and others wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t neceſſaries, without ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing reliefe from thoſe who are welthy. The reaſon here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of being, in that God being the Father of all men indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently, did creat the world and all things therein, for the Common profit of all men; and therefore who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne ſuperfluous riches to themſelues, without diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buting part of them to good
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:3282:66"/> and pious vſes, do contrary to the will of God therein, and conſequently do ſinne.</p>
               <p>Now, to come to that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther excuſe, that <hi>men are obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to prouide for Children,</hi> and <hi>that therefore they haue nothing to ſpare for any good vſes, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to redeeme themſelues from the future fyer of Purgatory.</hi> And in thus Apologizing for themſelues, they can rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily alledge that place of Scripture, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. <hi>Si quis ſuorum, &amp; maximè domestico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum curam non habet, fidem ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gauit, &amp; est infideli deterior; If any man hath not care of his owne, and eſpecially of thoſe of <pb n="103" facs="tcp:3282:66"/> his houſhould, he denyeth his fayth, and is worſe then an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this poore reaſon, ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed vnder the veyle of naturall affection, and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall care, I thus anſwere. I do not diſalow a moderate care to be taken for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion of Children; for he were an inhumane monſter who ſhould neglect the ſame. But this is it I ſay, to wit, for a man to be on the one ſyde ſo wholy abſorpt &amp; drunke in a thirſty purſuite of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall riches, for a ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous aduancement of his owne children; and on the <pb n="104" facs="tcp:3282:67"/> other ſyde, to be wholy ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligent, careles, &amp; incurious for the preuenting of the horrible flames of Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory.</p>
               <p>This I ſay, is that, which may well be ſtyled an inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible <hi>Lethargy</hi> in men. The <hi>Extremities</hi> I altogether diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, the <hi>Meane</hi> I imbrace. And according to this <hi>(O Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes)</hi> your ouer great ſol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>licitude in theſe matters, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of you will make ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous prouiſion and charges in erecting a ſecond Houſe for a yonger Sonne, and the like; becauſe they are neere to you, as being Proſemina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <pb n="105" facs="tcp:3282:67"/> from your owne loines; But your owne poore ſoules in the meane tyme you who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forget, as if they were but ſtrangers to you, or (as the Phraſe is) but of the halfe bloud: ſuch cecity &amp; blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in men is greatly to be pittied.</p>
               <p>Be not vnnaturall to your ſelues, in being naturall to your Children. Let your owne Soules (which are more neere to you, then any Children) haue at leaſt a <hi>Childes Portion.</hi> When you looke vpon your children, looke vpon them, not with an eye of an ouer-indulgent, <pb n="106" facs="tcp:3282:68"/> but of a Chriſtian Father: And then may ech of you ſay to your ſelues in an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward reflexe of your iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: <hi>I loue you all dearely, with a Paternall loue, but I loue my owne ſoule, more dearely. I will prouide for your temporall meanes in fitting manner, and according to my degree. But ſhall my ouer much care of your tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall aduancement impoueriſh my ſoule? O, God forbid!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What pleaſure will it be to my poore ſoule, lying burning in the most dreadfull flames of Purgatory, for bestowing of that ſuperfluity of meanes, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing otherwiſe bestowed for the
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:3282:68"/> good of my ſoule, might haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed me from thoſe flames? Will your ſelues thinke intenſly, of my ſuch calamitous state, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred by my ouer great loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you? and accordingly will you worke meanes, by prayers, ſuffrages, and Almes-deeds in my behalfe, for the leſsening of thoſe my torments? O, I feare you will not. And this I may probably gather, from the care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſse negligence in this point of many children towards other pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents being now dead. And how can I promiſe to my ſelfe more from you, then we ſee by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, other dead Parents haue receaued from their liuing chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren?</hi> 
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:3282:69"/> Let this be your ſpeach in the ſecret Cloſet of your harts, concerning your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
               <p>There is no Parent ſo kind, who would be content to ſuffer daily torments and rackings, to redeeme his ſonne from the like torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, to which by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miting ſome flagitious Cryme he ſtands ſubiect &amp; obnoxious. Is not then that Parent (I will not ſay halfe diſtracted, but) of moſt weake iudgment, who ſhall labour, and couet cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely to vndergoe moſt horrible torments (and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>parably far greater, then
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:3282:69"/> this world can affoard) and this not for freeing his ſonne from any paynes at all; but only that his children may liue in a more lautious, opu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, &amp; full manner, then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe they ſhould, though competent, and ſufficient meanes would notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding be left vnto them?</p>
               <p>For is it not infinitly far better for the Pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, to leaue his children, in fitting de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree and quality, furniſhed with temporall meanes, and withall himſelfe, by diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buting a good part of his ſtate in his life tyme to ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ends, wholy to preuent, <pb n="110" facs="tcp:3282:70"/> or at leaſt partly to diminiſh the paynes of <hi>Purgatory;</hi> then to leaue his iſſue in greater affluency and abundance of worldly riches, and himſelfe to continue many yeares in that inſufferable conflagra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of fyer; the grieuouſnes whereof truly to conceaue paſſeth our conceite? O,
<hi>Ante faciem frigoris eius quis ſustinebit? Pſal.</hi> 147.</p>
               <p>Thus far I haue thought good to draw out, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large this
<hi>Section,</hi> in ſtirring the mould about the roote of this ordinary pretence, &amp; excuſe of Parents prouiding for their Children; by reaſon
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:3282:70"/> that moſt Parents (to the great preiudice of their owne Soules) do ſhaddowe their want of Chriſtian Charity to others vnder this pretext; and therby they make their owne Children to become Enemyes to themſelues: and ſo it falleth out to be moſt true, as is aboue alledged by the foreſaid illuſtrious Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall: <hi>Inimici hominis, Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stici eius. Matth.</hi> 20.</p>
               <p>Yet before I conclude this <hi>Section,</hi> I only ſay; although according to the iudgment of the Philoſophers; <hi>No man knowes, what kind of loue that is which Parents beare to their <pb n="112" facs="tcp:3282:71"/> children, but he that hath chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren;</hi> notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding before I would endure an infinity of torments for their greater and more full aduancement, I would in part leſſen my temporall State, for the good of my owne Soule: for though Children be moſt neere to their Parents, yet that ſentence is moſt true: <hi>Tu tibi Primus, &amp; Vltimus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:3282:71"/>
               <head>A Perſuaſory Diſcourſe for the putting in practiſe the meanes (which are good Workes) for the auoyding of the paynes of Purgatory.
<hi>SECT. III.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN the two former Paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges are layed open, Firſt the Horrid atrocity of the paynes of Purgatory; Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the meanes how to preuent, at leaſt to leſſen &amp; mitigate them: It now fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, that I ſpend ſome leaues in a <hi>Paraeneticall</hi> (as I may terme it) or Perſuaſory <pb n="114" facs="tcp:3282:72"/> diſcourſe, therby to inuite Catholikes to put in practiſe the ſaid meanes, which are conducing for the preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of thoſe temporary dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full flames. And whereas theſe my ſpeaches are dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted chiefly to ſuch of you Catholikes, which are moſt ſlouthfull and ſluggiſh in the proſecution of the ſame meanes, I meane, in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of <hi>Good Workes.</hi> Therefore I muſt heere in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate you, to pardon my rudenes of ſtyle, ſince it beſt ſorteth to point forth (for words are the Images of things) your moſt deplora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:3282:72"/> ſtate herein. Dangerous wounds (you know) muſt haue deepe inciſions; And matter of Tragedy (for I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count yours to be ſuch) is to be deliuered in mournefull <hi>Accents.</hi> Neuer ought we in this caſe to forbeare the tou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ching of the member affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with a hard hand. O no. The Apoſtle indoctrinateth vs otherwiſe, in thoſe his fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorous and fiery words, 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. <hi>Praedica, Insta, oportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nè, importunè, argue, obſecra, increpa &amp;c.</hi> To ſuch Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liks, which are feruorous in the performance of good and pious Actions, this my
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:3282:73"/> ſpeach doth not extend.</p>
               <p>But here now I hould it conuenient to marſhall and range ſuch men into ſeuerall kinds, to which men this my Admonition belongeth. The firſt kind of theſe are ſuch, as are yet <hi>Schiſmatikes</hi> in the preſent courſe of their lyfe, and other Catholikes, who hertofore perhaps haue liued for many yeares in a <hi>Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall</hi> ſtate. Touching the firſt kind of actuall <hi>Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes;</hi> admitting, that before their death, they become truly penitent of their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer continuance in
<hi>Schiſme;</hi> for otherwiſe their ſoules <pb n="117" facs="tcp:3282:73"/> are infallibly to deſcend to Hell, not to <hi>Purgatory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But admitting (I ſay) the beſt; to wit, that they do dye in true repentance of their former ſinne, which only muſt proceed from the bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les Ocean of Gods mercy; Yet, what ineuitable Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and for how many yeares, do expect the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, if otherwiſe they ſeeke not to deliuer themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues thereof, in their owne lyfe tyme by good workes? This point will beſt appeare by diſcouering in part the atrocity of
<hi>Schiſme,</hi> and a <hi>Schiſmaticall</hi> lyfe. For the
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:3282:74"/> better explayning whereof I will inſiſt in the Authorities of the Holy Scripture, &amp; the moſt ancient Fathers.</p>
               <p>And to begin with Gods word, we thus read, <hi>Galat.</hi> 5.
<hi>The workes of the fleſh are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery, fornication, &amp; Sects:</hi> (meaning thereby <hi>Schiſmes) They which ſhall do ſuch things, ſhall not inherit the kingdome of God.</hi> And in reſpect of the ſtate of
<hi>Schiſme,</hi> the Church of God, is ſtyled in ſacred Writ: <hi>One ſheepfould (Ioan.</hi> 10.) <hi>One body (Rom.</hi> 12.) <hi>One Spouſe, (Cant.</hi> 6.) <hi>and one Doue.</hi> But now <hi>Schiſme,</hi> as comming of the Greeke ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be <pb n="119" facs="tcp:3282:74"/> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<hi>ſcindo,</hi> deuideth that which is one, into parts: Therefore as a member cut of from the whole body, cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to be a part of the ſaid body; ſo a <hi>Sciſmatike</hi> by open profeſſion of an Erroneous Religion, impugned by the Church of Chriſt, ceaſeth thereby to be a member of the Church of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>To deſcend to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; Marke how they pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſill out a
<hi>Schiſmatike,</hi> or <hi>Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me:</hi> I will vrge but two or three for breuity. <hi>S. Austin</hi> then thus writeth <hi>(l. de fide &amp; Symb. c.</hi> 20.) <hi>Schiſmatiks though they belieue the ſame
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:3282:75"/> points, which we belieue; yet through their diſſention they do not keep fraternall charity; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we conclude, that a Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike belongeth not to the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church, becauſe he loueth not his neighbour.</hi> Thus <hi>S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stin. Fulgentius</hi> thus teacheth,
<hi>(l. de fide ad Petrum c.</hi> 38. <hi>&amp;</hi> 39.)
<hi>Firmiſsimè tene &amp;c. Belieue for certayne, and doubt not, that not only Pagans, but alſo Iewes, Heretikes, &amp; Schiſmatikes, who dye out of the Catholike Church, are to goe to euerlasting fyer.</hi> To conclude,
<hi>S. Cyprian</hi> thus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerreth <hi>(l.</hi> 4 <hi>Epist.</hi> 9. <hi>ad Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent.) Qui cum Epiſcopo non ſunt, in Eccleſia non ſunt: who
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:3282:75"/> agree not with the Biſhop</hi> (mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſupreme Biſhop &amp; Paſtour of the Church) <hi>are not in Gods Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus we ſee, what is the iudgment both of Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture and of the ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, paſſed vpon the moſt dangerous ſtate of
<hi>Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiks.</hi> From whence we may infallibly conclude, that ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing the beſt, I meane, that <hi>Schiſmatiks</hi> do finally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent &amp; dye in ſtate of Grace, which is moſt doubtfull, conſidering their long inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate <hi>Schiſmaticall</hi> liues; yet what imminent temporall torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts (euen hanging ouer <pb n="122" facs="tcp:3282:76"/> their heads) are ready to ruſh vpon them, inſtantly vpon the ſeparation of the ſoule from the body, and to ſeize vpon their ſoules, for the ſatisfying of Gods Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice? But ſeeing the ſtate of <hi>Schiſmatikes</hi> is ſo deſperate &amp; dangerous, I am to be pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, if I ſharpen my pen more peculiarly againſt the <hi>Schiſmatikes</hi> of our owne Countrey.</p>
               <p>Heare then, you <hi>Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes of England,</hi> who for ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing your temporall goods, will endanger the loſſe of all eternall good; How much do you diſhonour (yea vili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy <pb n="123" facs="tcp:3282:76"/> God) by perſeuering in your <hi>Schiſmaticall</hi> ſtate? Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure your ſelues <hi>(You Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matikes)</hi> that it is not in your power to command at your pleaſure, ouer Tyme &amp; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance. God calleth euery one, but how often he will call, no man knoweth; and be you afrayd of that feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Sentence of his Diuine Maieſty: <hi>My People would not heare my voyce, and Iſraell would none of me; So I gaue them vp to the hardnes of their hartes. Pſal</hi> 81. O moſt dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Relegation!</p>
               <p>But admit, God will giue you tyme to repent; yet the
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:3282:77"/> ſtrength of your Armes is to weake to bend that
<hi>Virgam ferream</hi> of Gods Iuſtice, by the which he puniſheth with eternall damnation finall Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repentance, and chaſtizeth ſinne (if ſo all ſuch points be not with good workes cleared afore in this world) with temporary (but moſt inſupportable) paynes of <hi>Purgatory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But yet to make you to caſt a more feeling and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſe Introuerſion vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your owne moſt deplorable ſtates; Suppoſe a Natiue Subiect ſhould through ſome tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall reſpect and end, beare
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:3282:77"/> himſelfe moſt traitourouſly towards his King, daily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petrating ſome Act of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyalty, and euer banding himſelfe openly with other his profeſſed Enemies: how could this Man in reaſon thinke, that his ſubmiſſion could euer be ſufficient for his after reconciling to his Soueraigne, and obtayning Grace and fauour, &amp; future aduancement to honour &amp; Dignity? eſpecially if the King were of that ſeuere diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, as that he was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer accuſtomed to puniſh (though often in a lower degree then the offence de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued) <pb n="126" facs="tcp:3282:78"/> ech act of Diſloyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Diſobedience com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt him?</p>
               <p>And is not the ſtate of a <hi>Schiſmatike</hi> far more deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and dangerous? This man committeth ſpirituall Treaſon againſt <hi>the Diuine Maiesty,</hi> by his daily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating in Prayers and rytes, with the Preaching Members of an erroneous Church, Gods deſigned Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries: How then can he expect, with his ſo much gauled Conſcience, to arriue to Heauen without extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary acts of Mercy to the poore, and other workes of <pb n="127" facs="tcp:3282:78"/> Piety in this world, or of ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering moſt exquiſite and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vtterable torments in <hi>Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory?</hi> Conſidering God is iuſt, and ſeuerely chaſtizeth euery ſinne, committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him; <hi>Behould</hi> (ſayth he by his Prophet Iſay)
<hi>I will be reuenged vpon my Enemyes, &amp; will comfort my ſelfe in their destruction, Iſa.</hi> 1. And againe: <hi>God ſhall rayne ſnares of fyer v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon ſinners; Brimstone, with tempestuous winds, ſhalbe the portion of their Cuppe. Pſal.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>Poore wretch (I meane poore <hi>Schiſmatike</hi>) how wilt thou be able to ſuffer theſe inſufferable paynes, and this
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:3282:79"/> for many yeares at the beſt; that is, if finally thou dye in true Repentance of thy for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>Schiſmaticall</hi> Courſe, who with ſuch anxiety, toyle, &amp; impatie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce art accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed to endure the payne of the tooth-ach, or other torment in this world? And is the
<hi>Schiſmatike</hi> ſo ſenſible of a litle payne in this life, &amp; yet hopes he ſhall not be ſenſible of infinitly greater paynes in the life to come?</p>
               <p>Therefore now in tyme rayſe your ſelues out of this ſpirituall <hi>Lethargy,</hi> &amp; awake; ſince the longer you conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in this your deſperate <pb n="129" facs="tcp:3282:79"/> ſtate, you do but all that time (admitting you finally dye repentantly) euen heap fuell together for the nouriſhing of your flames in <hi>Purgatory.</hi> Remember the
<hi>Wiſemans</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10. <hi>Languor pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lixior grauat Medicum.</hi> You cannot but know, that du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring your ſtate in
<hi>Schiſme,</hi> you are wholy depriued of Gods Grace, by which we make clayme to Heauen; <hi>(Gratia Dei, vita aeterna. Rom.</hi> 6.) ſince you wilfully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue yours ſelues of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the Sacraments of Gods Church; which Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments our Sauiour hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted <pb n="130" facs="tcp:3282:80"/> in his Church, as the ordinary meanes, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duits, for the deriuing of Gods grace into mans ſoule.</p>
               <p>Well, I will cloſe this point of <hi>Schiſmatikes</hi> with this one aſſeueration: To wit, that a poore <hi>Motley foole</hi> (be you not offended, for I ſpeake the truth) to whome God hath afforded only the vſe of his fiue Senſes, is in far more happy ſtate, then you
<hi>Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matikes</hi> are. This ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (though moſt deſpicable in the eye of the world) as through want of the vſe of Reaſon, cannot merit; ſo he cannot demerit: You through your abuſe of <pb n="131" facs="tcp:3282:80"/> Reaſon, do not only, not me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; but in lieu thereof you increaſe the heape of your ſinnes, through a daily coa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceruation of your <hi>Schiſmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi> Tranſgreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. This man is infallibly freed from the paines of
<hi>Purgatory,</hi> much more of Hell: You are aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ſuffer the paines of <hi>Purgatory</hi> at leaſt, God grant (through your finall irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance) not the paynes of Hell.</p>
               <p>Briefly this man through the benefit of his Baptiſme, hath his
<hi>Originall ſinne</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled; &amp; as for <hi>Actuall ſinne,</hi> he ſtandes not obnoxious <pb n="132" facs="tcp:3282:81"/> thereto: You are indeed freed by your ablution in that ſacred Font, from <hi>origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſinne;</hi> but then you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale the worth &amp; Dignity therof, by your actuall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petrating of mortall ſinne. I ſpeake in the ſight of God, <hi>I had rather be one of theſe poore-rich fooles, ſo to call them, (for he is rich, who is aſſured of his inheritance of Heauen) then to be the greateſt, and most wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Schiſmatike in England; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reſolued to continue yeare after yeare, in this his most wicked courſe of Schiſme; Quid proderit homini, ſi vniuerſum mundum lucretur, anima vero <pb n="133" facs="tcp:3282:81"/> ſuae detrimentum patiatur? what ſhall it profit a man, if he gayne the whole world, and looſe his owne Soule? Matth.</hi> 16.</p>
               <p>Well, in this next place to touch a litle vpon ſuch, who are at this preſent actually Catholiks, yet haue perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red many yeares in a
<hi>Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall</hi> ſtate, before they were incorporated into the Catholike Church; what ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction and deeds of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Mercy to others are they bound to performe, to peeuent the paynes <hi>of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory,</hi> or els to endure them for many yeares? This partly appeareth, from the vgly <pb n="134" facs="tcp:3282:82"/> ſtate (ſo to call it) of a
<hi>Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matike,</hi> aboue in part deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed. And if he will not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme ſuch abſterſiue Acts of penance in his owne lyfe tyme, by contributing, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pitty, and relieuing of others; let him take heed, he fall not vpon that dreadfull ſentence of the Apoſtle, <hi>Iac.</hi> 2.
<hi>Iudicium ſine miſericordia ei, qui non fecerit miſericor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diam. Iudgment without mercy is to fall to him, who will not practiſe mercy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alas! Are you not men? Muſt you not once dye (and how ſoone God knoweth:) And are you not then to <pb n="135" facs="tcp:3282:82"/> render a moſt ſtrict accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for your fore-paſſed lyfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, euen to him, of whom it is ſaid for his moſt exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit and narrow ſearch into our ſinnes,
<hi>Scrutabor Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem in lucernis. Sophon.</hi> 1. <hi>I will ſearch the ſinnes of Ieruſalem with a Candle.</hi> And will you then be ſo negligent, and careles, in preuenting that dreadfull time? Since God is no accepter of Perſons, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will Riches, Worldly pompe, nor any other ſuch glorious miſeries help a ſoule ready to depart out of its bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, for the deliuering it <hi>from Purgatory,</hi> except great Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes-deeds
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:3282:83"/> (beſides other pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitentiall works) be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the life tyme.</p>
               <p>Well then, my poore, and deare <hi>Catholike,</hi> who for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeares, through thy wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked diſſimulation in matters of Religion, haſt moſt highly offended God; Imagine thy ſelfe, that at this very inſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, thou wert lying vpon thy death bed: (that bed, I ſay, which the
<hi>Prophet</hi> calleth, <hi>Lectum doloris, (Pſal.</hi> 40) <hi>the bed of griefe,</hi>) worne away with payne and ſicknes, &amp; not expecting to eſcape, but looking euery minute for thy laſt diſſolution; How
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:3282:83"/> would thy Iudgment be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered? and wouldſt thou not thus (in all likely-hood) reaſon and diſpute with thy owne Soule? <hi>True it is, I thanke God, of his moſt infinite and boundles Mercy, that as a straying ſheep, I am at length brought into Christs ſheep-fold, and I hope to dye (through the benefit of our Sauiours paſsion, and of the holy Sacraments) his ſeruant, and in state of Grace, and finally to enioy the intermi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nable ioyes of Heauen. But alas, though the guilt of Eternall damnation (incurred by my long former Schiſmaticall lyfe, &amp; by my many other infinite ſinnes) <pb n="138" facs="tcp:3282:84"/> as I hope, through Gods infinit mercy, be remitted; yet temporall puniſhment due for all my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſaid ſinnes, in most inexpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable torments of Purgatory doth expect me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My poore Soule muſt conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in thoſe burning Flames (how many yeares, his diuine Maiesty only knoweth) for the expiating of my ſaid ſinnes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I can arriue to Heauen. When I was in health, enioying my temporall ſtate in all fulnes, how eaſily with a voluntary re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquiſhing of a reaſonable part thereof to pious and religious vſes, could I haue auoyded (at least mitigated) theſe now im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:3282:84"/> and vnauoydable tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? Good god! where then were my Wits? The very plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man prouides for the tyme of Winter; yea the Ant (to the which we are ſent by Gods word (Prou.</hi> 6.) <hi>to be inſtructed) hoords graynes of Corne for his after ſustenance; And haue I ſo negligently carryed my ſelfe, as to lay vp before-hand no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion, againſt this tempestuous and rugged future storme? O beast, that I was! Sweet Ieſus, how far diſtant were my former courſe of lyfe and daily actions from euer thinking of this vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoydable danger? I haue liued many yeares in fulnes of state: I <pb n="140" facs="tcp:3282:85"/> haue beene labouring in laying out good ſummes of Siluer, to heap land to land for my Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to inherit. I haue liued (perhaps) in a most profuſe or wastfull manner; I haue ſpent to much, to gayne the deceitfull fauour of the world, in ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous apparell, exceeding my ſtate, in keeping an ouer waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full houſe, and in ouer great &amp; vnneceſſary Attendance about me. By meanes of ſome, or all of theſe extrauagant Courſes, I haue ſpent much; And yet not once did I euer thinke to bestow the twentith part of theſe ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous charges to pious vſes, for the preuenting of thoſe flames, <pb n="141" facs="tcp:3282:85"/> which within few dayes (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps few houres) my poore ſoule must ſuffer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O wretch that I am, that haue thus ſenſeleſly ſo neglected this fearefull day! Here now my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer pleaſures, and Iollity are come to their laſt end and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod. Gods Iuſtice muſt, and will be ſatisfyed; ſince nothing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyled and contaminated (except all the ruſt therof be afore fyled away) can enter into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heauen. Whither then now, being encompaſſed on ech ſyde with ſuch thornes of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, &amp; anxiety, ſhall I turne my ſelfe? To the world, and my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer pleaſures thereof? O God, <pb n="142" facs="tcp:3282:86"/> the remembrance of them is most nauſeous, and distastfull to me; ſince the fruition of them is a great cauſe of my future pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. To my former greatnes and fulnes of my temporall state? O, that I had beene ſo happy, as to haue made true benefit in tyme, of that Mammon of Iniquity, my wastfull ſpending whereof must giue fuell to that fyer! And we are taught, that, Diuitiae non proderunt in die vltimo. Prou.</hi>
11. <hi>To my Friends, Kyndred, &amp; former familiar acquaintance, which I ſhall leaue behind me in the World? Wo is me, they are as wholy negligent of their owne ſoules danger, concerning this <pb n="143" facs="tcp:3282:86"/> point, as my ſelfe haue beene. How then can I expect them to be ſolicitous &amp; carefull of myne?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To thee then alone (most mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull and heauenly Father) who art Pater miſericordiarum,</hi> (2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.) <hi>and who dost crowne vs in miſericordia &amp; miſerationi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus (Pſal.</hi> 102.) <hi>I do flye. Who tookeſt mercy of the Woman of Canaan, of Mary Magdalen, of the Publican, and of the thiefe hanging vpon the Croſſe. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the armes of thy ineffa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Compaſsion I caſt my ſelfe. Leſſen, (ô Leſſen) for thy owne honours ſake, and the bitter paſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion of thy most Deare Sonne, my Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, theſe tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall <pb n="142" facs="tcp:3282:87"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <pb n="143" facs="tcp:3282:87"/> 
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="144" facs="tcp:3282:88"/> paynes, which now wante for me. Let my preſent Compun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and Contrition of all my former ſinnes (through thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, &amp; Sons pretious death) ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riue to that aſcent and height, as that my Sauiour may ſay to me with the good thiefe; to day thou ſhalt be with me in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe. So shall thy Mercy thereby ouer-ballance thy Iustice; For to ſpeake in the Churches Dialect; Plus potes dimittere, quàm ego committere: and it is my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, that I read in holy Writ; Suauis est Dominus vniuerſis, &amp; miſerationes eius ſuper om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia opera eius, (Pſal.</hi>
144.) <hi>Our Lord is ſweet to all, and his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy <pb n="145" facs="tcp:3282:88"/> is aboue all his Workes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O that I had beene ſo happy, as to haue followed the whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome aduyce, giuen to me by way of Preſage in a little Treatiſe, entituled,</hi> An Antidot againſt Purgatory: <hi>I then did read it, but with a certaine curioſity, as thinking it nothing to belong to me. But (alas) I now find it to be a true Sybill, or Prophet of my future Calamitous ſtate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Well then, ſeeing my owne hower-glaſse is almost run out, let me turne my ſpeach to you (Deare Catholiks) in my health my chiefeſt Familiars; &amp; with whom I did most conſociate in my former pleaſures. There is no<pb n="146" facs="tcp:3282:89"/> difference betweene you and me, but the tyme preſent, and the tyme to come. You all muſt once be forced to this bed of ſorrow, and be brought to your last Sicknes. To you then, and to all others, who are negligent in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiding against this Day, I do di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect this my charitable Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition. You are yet in health, &amp; perhaps as improuident in laying vp ſpirituall riches againſt this fearefull day, as my ſelfe haue beene. O change your Courſe, whiles there is tyme. Let my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent state preach to you, &amp; ſuffer theſe my last dying words to giue lyfe to your future Actions; ſince they preach feelingly whoſe Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:3282:89"/> is their death-Bed. Be not in the number of thoſe ſenſles creatures, who are buryed ſo deep in earth, as that they haue no tast or feeling of things to come; Nolunt intelligere, vt benè a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant. (Pſal.</hi> 35.)</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Do now therefore (Deare Friends) do now, what you can. Now while you haue tyme, heap vp togeather, that ſpirituall Wealth, which will buy out all enſuing paynes; and turne the Current of your former ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous Charges, into the fayre streame of pious workes, that ſo it may affoard you water, for the quenchinge of thoſe raging Flames. Conſider how you ſhall <pb n="148" facs="tcp:3282:90"/> be conuented before the ſeuere Iudge, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whom nothing can be hidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Prophet ſaith: Tu cognouisti omnia, nouiſsima &amp; antiqua. (Pſal.</hi> 138.) <hi>He is not appeaſed with guifts, nor ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mtiteth excuſes, who out of his boundles mercy remitteth to vs (vpon our true repentance) the paynes of eternall damnation; but yet chastizeth vs with tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall puniſhment to ſatisfy his Iustice: miſericordia &amp; veritas obuiauerunt ſibi, iuſtitia &amp; pax oſculati ſunt. Pſal.</hi> 81. <hi>Therefore now begin to ſpread your ſelues in workes of Piety. Leſſen your temporall Pompe, deſcend in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward comportment vnder your <pb n="149" facs="tcp:3282:90"/> ſelues, and let your ſparing char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges by this meanes ſaued, ſerue to redeeme you from thoſe hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid flames, which are hereafter to inuade you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To theſe, and the like diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſolate and Tragicall la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations in the inward reflexe of thy foule <hi>(my deare Catholike)</hi> ſhalt thou in thy laſt Sicknes be driuen, if thou ſeeke not to preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the danger in tyme. Therefore Remember, <hi>that he is truly Wiſe, who laboreth to be ſuch in his health, as he wisheth to be found in Gods ſight, at the hower of his Death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But now to come to you<pb n="150" facs="tcp:3282:91"/> other Catholiks, who thogh you euer liued within the boſome of the Catholike Church; yet the ſtate of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of you is otherwiſe moſt deplorable, who though you dye in ſtate of grace (though many hundred Catholikes, through their owne vicious liues and finall irrepentance do not) yet your Caſe (with reference to the torments of <hi>Purgatory</hi>) is lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>table. Moſt of you are wholy heedles &amp; negligent in ſeeking by your good Workes, and Almes-deeds to auoyde
<hi>Purgatory.</hi> How many of you, whoſe meanes are great, might
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:3282:91"/> without any ſtay after your Death, euen poſt to Heauen by your Religious diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of a good part thereof; whereas others, through want of temporall meanes ſo to be diſtributed, muſt ſtay long in <hi>Purgatory?</hi> O, that Man ſhould be ſo treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to his owne Soule!</p>
               <p>It is daily obſerued (euen with griefe to all Zealous Catholikes) that many of you are ready to lay out great ſummes of ſiluer for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing of your temporall ſtates; That others of you, who are deuoted to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentments and pleaſures of <pb n="152" facs="tcp:3282:92"/> this World, to diſſipate a great part of your liuing in fruitles charges: Some in gallantry of apparell, others at Dyce, in Running-Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, in keeping waſtfull Chriſtmaſſes; your ſelues &amp; your Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany feeding moſt lautiouſly vpon all variety of curious meates &amp; wynes, whiles in the meane tyme your poore ſoules perhaps remayne, euen hunger-ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued (as I may ſay) for want of ſpirituall nouriſhment. In all which courſes it is be feared, that many, euen mortall ſinnes, are by you committed, of the which, <pb n="153" facs="tcp:3282:92"/> though you after haue pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged your ſelues by the holy Sacrament of Confeſſion, yet what reckonings are there remayning touching the temporall puniſhments attending ſuch your ſinnes? which either in this world muſt be taken away by great ſatisfaction performed by you, or els all ſuch ruſt muſt be purged and burned away in the Horrible Flames of Purgatory.</p>
               <p>Therefore it is not a ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Imprudency; It is not a weakenes of the vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; It is not a bare miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the iudgment: But it
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:3282:93"/> is meere Lunacy &amp; Madnes in you, thus to aduance tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral reſpects either of gaine or pleaſure, before the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenting of thoſe inſufferable torments. And if any of you, who are of great ſtates, do leaue a hundred pounds at your deaths to be prayed for, O, you thinke, you haue made a large and ample ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction for all your ſinnes, and that after thoſe Prayers are performed, you are ſure inſtantly to goe to Heauen. A ſelfe flattering, and credu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous conceit! Thinke of the cuſtome of the Venerable Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of the ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Church, <pb n="155" facs="tcp:3282:93"/> who were vſed to tye a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to performe penance ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen yeares, for the commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting but of one mortal ſinne: How much different was their Iudgment, from your Iudgment herein?</p>
               <p>Againe, what ſmall a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion hath this ſo niggard an Almes-deeds of yours, with that of the man reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to lyfe, and recorded by
<hi>Venerable Bede,</hi> who gaue the third part of his goods to the poore, the reſt to his wyfe and Children; of whome <hi>Cardinall Bellarmyne</hi> did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue ſpeake in the firſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of this booke? Or how
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:3282:94"/> ſtands your Charity to good vſes with reference to
<hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaeus,</hi> ſpoken of in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, <hi>Luc.</hi> 19. who after he had ſeene <hi>Christ,</hi> gaue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly the halfe of his ſtate to the poore. Truly I ſpeake in all ſincerity; I knew two Gentlemen in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, who were but Eſquyers, (though of good ſtates) and yet at the tyme of their deaths (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides many other moſt good and holy workes done by them in their life tyme) the one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did leaue to good vſes fifteene hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred pounds, and the other a thouſand Markes. Therefore let ſuch
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:3282:94"/> Catholiks, who are carefull of their Soules-good, be ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly emulous of ſuch me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s deuotion and charity; and let them remember, that ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>S. Chyſostome (ſerm.</hi> 37. <hi>ad pop. Antioch.) Non dare, ſed copiosè dare, Eleemoſyna est.</hi> But to proceed.</p>
               <p>If any of you, vpon your iuſt Demerits, were to be racked for diuers moneths togeather; or if any of you were in the higheſt degree afflicted with ſome Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall payne; what would you not giue (if it were in your power) to redeeme your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues from theſe torments?
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:3282:95"/> And yet the firſt of theſe pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes might endure through the Clemency of the Prince, but few moneths (perhaps but few dayes) the other could not endure many yea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res, through the extremity of the payne (for
<hi>nullum vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentum eſt perpetuum:</hi>) And will you then be ſo leaden, ſtupid, and dull in iudgment, as willingly, and affectedly to vndergoe (it being in your power, by abandoning in your lyfe tyme a little Droſſe, to preuent them) ſuch paynes for many yeares (perhaps for many hundred of yeares;) in reference and <pb n="159" facs="tcp:3282:95"/> compariſon of which, all the greateſt torments in this world (in the iudgment of the ancient Fathers) are to be reputed, as ſhaddowes, or <hi>tipes</hi> of paynes? where is ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s vnderſtanding, where is the light of his Reaſon? But it ſeemes, they are exiled, and in their roome, are imbraced a moſt ſordid &amp; earthly reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of temporall, &amp; fading vanities.</p>
               <p>Therefore I may well here demand; Are ſuch perſons Catholikes? Are they Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s? yea are they men? who thus be trample withall ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>releſſnes, and ſupine neglect <pb n="160" facs="tcp:3282:96"/> the good of their owne ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, and rauell out their tyme in idle toyes and pleaſures? Alas! what are riches, great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of ſtate, a needles frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of temporall pleaſures, or that, which you call your reputation &amp; honour (which with-draw many from do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of good deeds) able to performe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Syr Iohn Oldcastle</hi> being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probated of his Cowardly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and thereby reputed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorious, replyed; <hi>If through my perſuyte of Honour, I ſhall fortune to looſe an Arme, or a Leg in the wars, can Honour re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>store to me my lost Arme, or <pb n="161" facs="tcp:3282:96"/> legge?</hi> In like manner I heere ſay to you, <hi>Catholikes:</hi> Can your Riches, your worldly pompe and pleaſures, or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity of your Houſe, and Family redeeme your Soules out of <hi>Purgatory?</hi> Or can this poore weake blaſt of wind or ayre, which you call your reputation (conſiſting in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens words, paſſed v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon you) coole the heate of thoſe burning flames? No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſſe, ſince theſe toyes (through your abuſe of them) ſhall ſerue, as bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, the more to blow the Flames of
<hi>Purgatory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will vrge one reaſon,<pb n="162" facs="tcp:3282:97"/> which ſhall make you <hi>(negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Catholikes)</hi> to bluſh, and withall to grow pale; for it ſhall force you to be aſhamed of your incredible neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in this great buſines heere treated of; and it ſhall put you (if ſo Gods grace be in you) in extreme feare of your future Calamity. I will take it from the examples of certaine moſt learned, pious, and ancient Fathers. The Fathers ſhalbe theſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>S. Austin, S. Ambroſe, S. Gregory,</hi> and
<hi>S. Bernard;</hi> all whoſe pens were guyded by the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S Ambroſe</hi> through the <pb n="163" facs="tcp:3282:97"/> extremity of his feare of the flames of Purgatory, thus writeth (<hi>Serm.</hi> 20.
<hi>in Pſal.</hi> 118.) <hi>I ſhalbe ſearched &amp; exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined as lead, in this fyer, till all the lead be melted away &amp;c. S. Austin</hi> through his fearefull and ſtrong apprehenſion of this fyer, thus breaketh out in words (<hi>in explic. Pſal.</hi> 37.) <hi>O Lord, let me be made ſuch, as that my Correction ſhall not be needfull to be increaſed with that purging fyer, in reſpect of ſuch men, qui ſalui erunt, ſic ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men quaſi per ignem.</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine <hi>S. Austin</hi> thus further ſaith (<hi>l</hi> 50.
<hi>homil.</hi> 16.) <hi>O how happy are they, that who liuing
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:3282:98"/> well, and contented with neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary riches to their bodies, libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall of their owne, chast in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and not cruell to others, do redeeme themſelues from this fiery Fornace?</hi> Of which fyer the ſaid <hi>S. Austin</hi> thus ſaith: <hi>in Pſal.</hi> 27. <hi>Grauior erit hic ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, quàm quis poteſt pati in hac vita. This fyer shalbe more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable, then any man can ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in this lyfe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S. Gregory</hi> thus writeth (<hi>in Pſal.</hi> 3.
<hi>Poenit.) I esteeme the purging fyer (though it be tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitory) to be more intollerable, then all tribulations, which in this life may be ſuffered; there<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore I do not only deſire, not to <pb n="165" facs="tcp:3282:98"/> be rebuked in the fury of eternal damnation; but alſo I great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly feare to be purged in the wrath of tranſitory Correction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, to come to <hi>S. Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi> whoſe trembling penne through feare of the paynes of <hi>Purgatory,</hi> thus diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth: (<hi>Serm. de ſex tribul.</hi> 16. <hi>&amp;</hi> 55. <hi>in Cant.) O would to God, that ſome man would now before hand, prouide for my head a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of water, and to myne eyes a fountayne of teares; that ſo perhaps the burning fyer should take no hold, where run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning teares had clenſed before.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now to reflect a little vpon the Worth of theſe
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:3282:99"/> foure former alledged Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; and then to draw our inference and deduction. <hi>S Ambroſe</hi> for his learning (he writing many bookes in defence of the Chriſtian Fayth) as alſo for his ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of lyfe, obtayned the title of being called <hi>(per Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellentiam) One of the foure Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Primitiue Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S. Austin</hi> (gayning the like title) was of that emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency for learning and pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that <hi>S. Ierome,</hi> thus extol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth him: <hi>(Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>Ep.</hi> 25. <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter opera August.) I haue all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes reuerenced thy Sanctity with that honour, which is fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting;
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:3282:99"/> and I haue loued our Lord and Sauiour dwelling in thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus much briefly of <hi>S. Auſtin,</hi> whoſe infinite pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, labour, and ſtudy (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides his extraordinary ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes in his conuerſation &amp; courſe of lyfe) in writing of ſo many, and ſo great
<hi>Tomes,</hi> with ſuch wonderfull per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of iudgment &amp; lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and all in defence of the Chriſtian and Catholike Faith, might ſeeme in the eye of many, to be ſufficient to expiate the temporall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment due for his ſinnes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S. Gregory</hi> was our <hi>Apostle,</hi> firſt planting Chriſtianity in <pb n="168" facs="tcp:3282:100"/> England, and of that Piety, as that
<hi>M. Godwin</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant (<hi>in his Catalogue of Biſhops. pag.</hi> 3.) thus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth him: <hi>That bleſsed &amp; holy Father S. Gregory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To come to <hi>S. Bernard:</hi> This bleſſed man (as
<hi>Oſian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der witneſſeth in his Epitome p.</hi> 309.) was an Abbot, authour of many monaſteries, both in France &amp; Flanders, inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuting
<hi>a Religious Order</hi> in Gods Church: Yea he was eminent for working of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles; of whom in regard of his piety of life, euen <hi>D. Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker</hi> our Aduerſary (<hi>lib. de Eccl. pag.</hi> 338.) thus cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brateth
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:3282:100"/> his worth: <hi>Ego qui dem Bernardum verè fuiſſe ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum existimo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, if theſe foure moſt worthy ſhining Lamps in the Church of God (or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo many bright ſtars in the celeſtiall Spheare) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable for learning, and more remarkable for piety and deuotion; they ſpending their whole tyme in writing in defence of the true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; be tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pling vnder their feet all temporall Honours and Preferments; liuing moſt chaſtly in Purity of body; &amp; wearing themſelues out in Faſting, Prayer, and ſeuerely <pb n="170" facs="tcp:3282:101"/> puniſhing their owne fleſh: Yf theſe men I ſay) notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all this their rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous courſe to fleſh &amp; bloud did ſtand in ſuch feare and horrour of the torments of
<hi>Purgatory</hi> (as we ſee aboue, by their owne words and writings, they did;) what then <hi>(My deare Catholickes)</hi> may be ſaid of moſt of you, who enioy the pleaſures of the world, pamper your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, liue in great riches and abundance, &amp; yet do thinke to eſcape the flames of that fyer? what is this, but mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and incredible partiality in the higheſt degree; you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <pb n="171" facs="tcp:3282:101"/> thus become <hi>Paraſytes</hi> to your owne ſelues, in thus flattering your owne moſt fearefull ſtate?</p>
               <p>But it may be, there are ſome of you, who, ſo you may enioy Heauen eternally in the end, become thereby leſſe carefull of preuenting the temporall paynes of <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory,</hi> ſleighting the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of them. But <hi>S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> ſhall diſcouer this vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, who thus diſcourſeth of this point, <hi>ſerm.</hi> 41. <hi>de ſanctis. Some vſe to ſay, I care not great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly how long ſoeuer I stay in paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing this fyer; ſeeing at the laſt, I ſhall attayne to life euerlaſting.</hi> 
                  <pb n="172" facs="tcp:3282:102"/> To which words <hi>S. Austin</hi> thus anſwereth: <hi>But alas, (deare Brother) Let no man ſay thus, for that this Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fyer is more ſharpe, then any puniſhment, which in this lyfe can be ſeene, imagined, or felt. And wheras it is ſaid of the day of Iudgment: That one day ſhalbe as a thouſand yeares, and a thouſand yeares as one day; how doth any man know, whether his paſſage through this fyer be for dayes, months, or perhaps yeares? And he, that will now be loath to put one of his fingers into bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning fyer, ought to feare the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that fyer, though it were but for a litle tyme. Therefore <pb n="173" facs="tcp:3282:102"/> let euery man labour with all his force, that he may auoyde mortall ſinnes, which caſt men into Hell; and to redeeme leſſer ſinnes by good workes, ſo as no part of them remayne to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed by that fyer.</hi> And then a litle after in the ſame place: <hi>Who commit litle, and daily ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, let them not ceaſe daily to redeeme them with good works; to wit, by continuall Prayer, fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Fastings, &amp; large Almes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus this bleſſed Father ſeriouſly meditateth in the ſecret of his ſoule vpon this point. What may we ſay of ſuch men, as read this, and are nothing moued there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with? <pb n="174" facs="tcp:3282:103"/> Truly ſuch men may be thought to haue but the outward ſhape, or faces of men; that is, they weare fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Cloaths, they talke, they walke togeather, they buſy their minds in needles toyes; but as for the true vſe of
<hi>Reaſon</hi> (wherein the eſſence of man conſiſteth) ſo far forth as it may become ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicable to the aduancement and ſpirituall good of their ſoules, they participate in their actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s more with beaſts who want ſoules, then with <hi>Rationall Creatures:</hi> A griefe not to be expreſſed, but in moſt deplorable <hi>Threnes</hi> and
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:3282:103"/> Lamentations.</p>
               <p>Nay, I dare be bold to ſay, that <hi>Beasts</hi> ſeeme to haue greater practiſe of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> then diuers of theſe men haue. Strike a Horſe, or an Aſſe once or twyce, or thruſt him into a deep or dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous hole, out of which he can hardly get; he will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue ſuch
<hi>Feare</hi> thereof, as that he will for a long tyme after ſeeke to auoyde both the ſtroakes, and the hole: And yet, where the Scripture, the teſtimonies of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and holy Fathers, the ſeuerall miracles exhibited in proofe of the torments of <pb n="176" facs="tcp:3282:104"/>
                  <hi>Purgatory,</hi> do fully proclame the horriblenes of thoſe pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, diuers <hi>Catholikes</hi> who are infallibly hereafter to endure the ſame paynes (if ſo they make no preuention in their lyfe tyme) haue no <hi>Feare, no Senſe, no Feeling thereof.</hi> O God, that <hi>Men</hi> ſhould thus ceaſe to be <hi>Men,</hi> and <hi>Beaſts</hi> (after a certaine manner) ſhould ſtep in their place.</p>
               <p>Well, I will conclude this my diſcourſe to you <hi>(Worthy Catholikes)</hi> humbly beſee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ching you, euen for the moſt precious, and bitter Paſſion of our Lord and Sauiour, &amp; for the future good of your
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:3282:104"/> owne ſoules, to caſt your eye vpon all the Premiſſes ſet downe in this ſmal Treatiſe, and haue a feeling Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration both of the extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the paynes, and of the infallible authorities pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the vndoubted certay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nety of thoſe paynes; and do not ſuffer your iudgments to fluctuate or wauer, touching the certainty of them. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I will only demand, Is there a <hi>Heauen?</hi> Is there a
<hi>Hell?</hi> Is there a <hi>Purgatory?</hi> Yf you belieue theſe things to haue a true and reall being, (as no doubt infallibly you do) where then (through <pb n="178" facs="tcp:3282:105"/> your ſo much ſleighting of them) is your Iudgment? If you hould them (as God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid) but as intentionall and aery Speculations of the braine, where is your Fayth? And a moſt miſerable Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction it is, whether a man will be damned for all eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, for want of practiſing neceſſary points of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion; or through want of Fayth.</p>
               <p>But before I end this paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage I will turne my penne, but withall gentle, and ſof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in part my ſtyle, in reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of the Perſons to which I will direct theſe few enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <pb n="179" facs="tcp:3282:105"/> lynes. To you then <hi>(great Catholicke Ladyes)</hi> and other <hi>Catholicke Gentle-women</hi> of worth (to whom in regard of my Sexe, I may be the more bold to ſpeake freely) whoſe preſent Widdowed ſtates by reaſon of your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed Husbands, ſtand en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched with more then ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary affluency (during your liues) of lands, money, and other temporall goods: You I ſay
<hi>(Noble Ladyes, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of Worth)</hi> though you be weake in Nature, yet know your owne ſtrength, and what great matters du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring your Widowhoods you <pb n="180" facs="tcp:3282:106"/> are able, through Gods aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance to performe, for the freeing you from the flames of <hi>Purgatory:</hi> and remember, that howſoeuer the nycenes &amp; delicacy of diuers of you be ſuch, as that in this world, you can brooke nothing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing to you; yet in the next world, admitting you dye in ſtate of Saluation, you muſt infallibly vndergo thoſe horrible flames (ſo much ſpoken of in theſe leaues) except by your cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritablenes (and this in a moſt full degree) you redeeme thoſe paynes.</p>
               <p>O what good Workes <pb n="181" facs="tcp:3282:106"/> might you do during your Widdowhoods? And yet I feare, you are moſt forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full therein. Many of you (I know) are ready to beſtow a hundred Marks, or more, vpon one gowne; and that gowne muſt not ſerue two yeares, but another (as char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geable) muſt inſtantly be had. Agayne, ſome of you will be content to loſe a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred marks, or more, in one night at Gleeke; and will weare about your necks Iewels, worth many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of pounds.</p>
               <p>O cut of theſe needles &amp; fruitles charges, and beſtow
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:3282:107"/> a good part thereof vpon your Soules, with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſnes of good and ſatisfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing works, though your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies in part be depriued of ſuch glorious Ornaments. There is none of you, but beſides your greater ſinnes, you daily commit leſſer ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes; for it is ſaid in holy Writ, <hi>Prou.</hi> 24. <hi>The lust man ſhall fall ſeauen tymes a day.</hi> How many idle, and vnne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſary thoughts and words paſſe from you, but in one day? and yet you muſt make ſatisfaction for euery ſuch thought or word, either here or in <hi>Purgatory,</hi> before you
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:3282:107"/> can arriue to Heauen. For it is ſayd, <hi>Prou.</hi>
19. <hi>They ſhall render an account of euery idle Word, in the day of iudgment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now then in tyme of your Widowhoods, lay out a great part of your riches to ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall vſury (as I may terme it) for the good of your Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les. I did know a yong gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle-woman, now dead: ſhe was left by her deceaſed Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two thouſand pounds, and better in portion. She in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to mary (and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her death ſhe did) yet before ſhe would ſubiect her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and her ſtate to any man, (beſides diuers good
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:3282:108"/> acts before) ſhe gaue at one tyme (I ſpeake of certaine and particular knowledge) three hundred pounds of her portion away, to the brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vp of poore ſchollers beyond the Seas; ſaying thus to herſelfe; <hi>If I ſhalbe content to enthrall my ſelfe, &amp; ſeauenteene hundred pounds at least, to the will of a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, who I know not how he will vſe me; haue I not reaſon to giue three hundred pounds away to my owne Soule, for his ſake, who will not ſuffer a cup of could water giuen in his name, to be vnrewarded?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is an Example wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy <pb n="185" facs="tcp:3282:108"/> of your taking notice of, thereby to put you in mind, to remember to preuent the flames of
<hi>Purgatory,</hi> during the tyme of your Widow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods. For if you be not ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citous thereof before your ſecond mariage, when your ſtates are in your owne diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſall; it is much to be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that your future Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands will bridle you of all ſuch (though moſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) charges. This Example may alſo be worthily a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident for all other yong Catholike gentle-women of great portions, to prouide for the good of their ſoules, <pb n="186" facs="tcp:3282:109"/> before they tye themſelues in mariage to any one.</p>
               <p>Well <hi>(Worthy Ladyes)</hi> let a woman once preach to women, and ſince you are Women. Imitate that <hi>Bleſſed Woman</hi> ſo much celebrated for her charity to others, in Gods holy writ, <hi>Prou.</hi> 31.
<hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ſuam aperuit inopi, &amp;c. She opened her hands to thoſe that wanted, and ſtretched out her armes to the poore;</hi> and thereupon it followeth of her in the ſaid word of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Et ridebit in die nouiſsimo; and ſhe ſhall laugh at the last day,</hi> That is, at the day of her death ſhe ſhall reioyce: and ſo <pb n="187" facs="tcp:3282:109"/> 
                  <hi>(Noble Ladyes, and others)</hi> it is in your power (if your ſelues will) to enioye the like felicity and retaliation, for your workes of charity, with her. And with this I giue a full cloſe to this my <hi>Exhortative Diſcourſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>Certaine examples of good works to be practiſed, for the auoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Purgatory, propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Authour of this Treatiſe.
<hi>SECT. IV.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE firſt of theſe <hi>Good Workes,</hi> ſo much wiſhed
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:3282:110"/> by me, ſhalbe not only in a mans priuate Deuotions &amp; Prayers; but alſo by ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of others of our Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Clergy (though e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of their owne moſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy propenſion and loyalty herein, I know they are not wanting) to pray for his <hi>Maiesty of England,</hi> our moſt gratious <hi>King,</hi> and for his worthy <hi>Queene,</hi> and their Royall Iſſue.</p>
               <p>This is the Duty, which all Subiects (of what Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion ſoeuer) ought to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme; and the performance thereof is a pleaſing, &amp; moſt gratefull ſpirituall Sacrifice <pb n="189" facs="tcp:3282:110"/> to the
<hi>Diuine Maiesty,</hi> and a good meanes (among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) to expiate our former Tranſgreſſions; <hi>Thus ſhall ech of vs feare the Lord, and honour the King. Prou.</hi> 24. And, <hi>giue to Ceſar, what is Ceſars. Matth.</hi> 22. For if the Prophet <hi>Ieremy</hi> (ſterned by Gods holy ſpirit, and therefore ſpoake the truth) commanded the
<hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lits,</hi> being brought into Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuity to <hi>Babylon,</hi> to pray for the good ſtate thereof, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them; <hi>In the peace ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, you ſhall haue peace. Ierem.</hi> 29. And if further alſo the
<hi>Iſraelites</hi> be counſelled by God in his holy Writ, to
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:3282:111"/> pray for the life of <hi>Nabucho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donoſor,</hi> and his ſonne <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſar. Baruch</hi> 1. How much more Reaſon then, haue all Prieſts, and Catholikes in England, euen to beſiege the eares of God with their dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and inceſſant Prayers and impetrations, for the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and temporall good of their King <hi>Charles?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Since the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> then prayed for their Enemy; We pray for our Dread Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne. They for him, who did lead them into Captiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: We for him, who keepes vs in liberty, peace, &amp; tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity. They for a meere <pb n="191" facs="tcp:3282:111"/> ſtranger and Idolater; We being Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, for our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Chriſtian Prince. Final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they for a forrayne Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: We for our owne Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, in which we are bred &amp; brought vp, and to which we owe <hi>Omnes omnium chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates:</hi> So willingly we muſt remember, that it is ſaid, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. <hi>We ought to be ſubiect to the King, as excelling.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore in regard of ſo worthy a worke, which euen in duty ought to be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by all Engliſh Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes and Prieſts; I the poore authour of this Treatiſe, will make bold, though a woman
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:3282:112"/> to Perſonate all the Engliſh Prieſts and good Catholikes in my ſelfe, and will offer vp to the Higheſt (in behalfe of vs all) this our moſt zealous and daily prayer: <hi>God preſerue with his eye of Vigilancy, and care our moſt Noble Prince King Charles, and his most illustrious Queene, and most worthy Iſsue. God grant him to proſper in all true felicity, both temporall and ſpirituall; and giue him the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledg that he may in his Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours perpetuate his Iſſue from generation to generation: That ſo of him it may be ſayd with the Prophet, Pſal.</hi>
127. <hi>Filij tui ſicut nouellae oliuarum, in circuitu <pb n="193" facs="tcp:3282:112"/> menſae tuae. And grant, that in the cloſe of their liues, they may all leaue the Stage or Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of this world with ſpirituall Trophees and Triumphs, for the gayning of that Celeſtiall King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; in compare of which, all the kingdomes vpon the Earth deſerue not to be Types or adum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brations.</hi> And, <hi>to this my vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned Prayer, I wiſh all good Engliſh Priests, and Catholikes to ſay, Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now I will I deſcend to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pious deeds, and ſuch as conſiſt in charges of ſiluer. And heere I will inſiſt (by way of Example) in certaine courſes taken by diuers of <pb n="194" facs="tcp:3282:113"/> the more earneſt Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, whoſe intentions therein (ſuppoſing their Religion were true) are moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable. I here may be the more bould to reſt in ſuch examples (I hope) without offence to any Proteſtant Reader (which willingly I labour to auoyde,) becauſe they are warranted by the Proteſtants owne practiſe, though in a different Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. Therefore their actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s for the aduancement of their Religion, may be a ſpur and incitement to vs, to practiſe the like actions for the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of our Catholike Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, <pb n="195" facs="tcp:3282:113"/> which is moſt Ancient and infallible.</p>
               <p>For no ſmall diſhonour it would be to vs Catholikes, that thoſe words of ſacred writ ſhould be auerred here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in of them and vs:
<hi>Filij huius ſaeculi prudentiores filijs lucis in ſua generatione ſunt. Luc.</hi> 16. <hi>The children of this world are more wiſe in their generation, then the Children of light.</hi> For ſhall ſuch men, whoſe Fayth euen depreſſeth the merit of <hi>Good Workes,</hi> exceed the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes in the practiſe of their ſuppoſed <hi>Good Workes?</hi> O no. Let therfore our owne practize of <hi>Good Workes</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:3282:114"/> a <hi>Scholia,</hi> to paraphraze our doctrine, &amp; beliefe tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching <hi>Good Workes.</hi> And how prepoſterous would it be, that our Aduerſaries putting no confidence in <hi>Good Works,</hi> ſhould neuertheleſſe in their owne iudgments be ready to performe them? We, who put confidence in them, as receauing their worth from the Merits of Chriſt his Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and his promiſſe of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to them (&amp; not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe) yet ſhould be ſlow in the operation of them? Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore may we not bluſh, that our owne cold remiſſnes in good actions, ſhould become
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:3282:114"/> a foyle to their greater ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Actions of that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture?</p>
               <p>Well then, to deſcend to particulars: We obſerue, that the more forward Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, fynding Youths (though meere ſtrangers vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them) of pregnancy and hope to be Schollars, will ſtrayne themſelues &amp; open their purſes, to maintayne them in our engliſh Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities; that finally they may become Miniſters, thereby more &amp; more to diſſeminate in the Realme their owne Proteſtant Religion. Now ſeeing the Catholike Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion <pb n="198" facs="tcp:3282:115"/> is only true, for <hi>Vna fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, vnum Baptiſma, Epheſ.</hi> 4. how meritorious and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing is it in the ſight of God, for you to practize the like Charity to yo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g poore ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of hopefull expectation, for their bringing vp in ſuch places of literature, as that when they haue ended their ſtudies, they may be ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceable in the Catholike Church for the general good of others?</p>
               <p>I inſtance (for example) in a pregnant yong boy of ſeauenteene, or eighteene yeares of age; This boy through want of meanes, for
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:3282:115"/> his better preferment is to become a Seruingman, a Clarke, a Prentiſe, or at the beſt (indeed the worſt) a Miniſter; In all which ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, conſidering the preſent ſtreme of Proteſtancy in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, his ſoule is in all like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyhood to periſh eternally, for his not dying in a true Fayth, and Religion. Now here obſerue the wonderfull difference, riſing from the performing, or omitting of ſuch a charitable deed. Yf ſuch a boy ſtay in England, then is his ſoule (as aboue is ſaid) in great perill of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally periſhing, through his
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:3282:116"/> profeſſing of an erroneous Fayth: Yf he be Catholikly brought vp, and ſent ouer the ſea's, he is to be inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in the only ſauing Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Faith, to the moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pefull Saluation of his ſoule.</p>
               <p>Yf he be here ſent to our Engliſh Vniuerſities, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally become a Miniſter; he then, not only looſeth his owne ſoule, but is to be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, will be the cauſe of the euerlaſting perdition of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other mens Soules, by his enuenoming, and infecting their Iudgments with his owne Religion: Yf he be brought vp in Catholike <pb n="201" facs="tcp:3282:116"/> places, beyond the Seas, and proceed forward in his courſe, he then (liuing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſtrict courſe of his vndertaken Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,) not only ſaueth his owne Soule, but is a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate Inſtrument vnder God, for the ſauing of many other mens ſoules partly by practiſing his function a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ſuch as be already Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes; and partly by his perſuaſion (if ſo he proue learned,) of others yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining Proteſtants, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the Roman Catholike Fayth.</p>
               <p>And thus if you obſerue, <pb n="202" facs="tcp:3282:117"/> either the preuenting of the great Hurt, and <hi>Euill,</hi> which is in likely-hood to come by the youthes taking the one courſe of life; or the great
<hi>Spirituall good</hi> to himſelfe &amp; others, by his vndergoing the other State: You may thinke your ſiluer employed to ſuch an Act, to be moſt happily layed out; Aſſuring your ſelues, that the worke of the
<hi>Euill</hi> here preuented, and the <hi>Good</hi> here performed (&amp; all originally vnder <hi>God,</hi> by your meanes) ſhall find a great retaliation at Gods moſt mercifull hands, both for the increaſe of your me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:3282:117"/> as alſo for the expiating of your ſinnes, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe is to be performed in <hi>Purgatory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Why then therfore ſhould ſuch of you, as be of the greater Ranke and beſt abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, be ſlow in practizing workes of this nature? Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now, while you haue tyme, lay wayte by all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient meanes to enquyre after ſuch occaſions; Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when ſuch a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar worthy Act may often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes be performed with leſſer charges, then diuers of you wil beſtow vpon a good ſuite of apparel. O the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raile
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:3282:118"/> and inueſt your Soules with ſuch good workes; and be leſſe chargeable in gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous attire for your bodies. I do aſſure you, if I had great and abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dant meanes for the practizing of the workes of Piety, I had rather make choyce to diſtribute to this vſe of prouiding and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of hopeful youths in learning, to the end aboue expreſſed, then to any other particular End whatſoeuer. For if neither any places of Reſidence beyond the Seas had beene prouided, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with ſufficient main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance for the bringing vp <pb n="205" facs="tcp:3282:118"/> of Engliſh Schollers; nor that there had beene any Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, who would haue ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned their purſes to this no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble End, Catholike Religion had beene vtterly extinct many yeares ſince, in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland.</p>
               <p>This Zeale of many good Catholikes both dead (and no doubt, aliue) in this point, is the fuell, that hath nouriſhed, and kept in, the fyer of Catholike Religion in our owne Country for many yeares paſt. Since if Youths were not ſent ouer to be (after their ſtudies en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded) created Prieſtes, how <pb n="206" facs="tcp:3282:119"/> could the profeſſion of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Religion continue in theſe ſo great ſtormes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs? Therefore what a great and inexplicable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort will it be to you in your laſt Sicknes, euen for ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of your temporall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, when you ſhall remember, that wheras ſuch, or ſuch a pregnant youth was in the high way of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and of ouerthrowing his owne, and other mens ſoules alſo, if he had procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in his former intended Courſe of life; yet you (through your charity) in laying out a little peece of <pb n="207" facs="tcp:3282:119"/> money, did vnder God, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by reſcue the ſayd youth, euen out of the Deuills iawes, and haue beene a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond meanes of ſauing both the youths owne ſoule, &amp; of the ſoules of diuers others?</p>
               <p>This being ſo, let me then intreat you <hi>(Most worthy Catholikes)</hi> euen for our Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uiours ſake (who gaue not ſiluer (as is heere only expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted) but his moſt precious bloud, for the ranſoning of all ſoules out of the Deuills poſſeſſion) that you would caſt a moſt ſerious, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſe conſideration of this one point. And thus far tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching <pb n="208" facs="tcp:3282:120"/> this particular kind of Almes-deeds.</p>
               <p>Only this much more I will annex, as an <hi>Appendix</hi> to the former, that I could wiſh the moſt able of you in temporall ſtate, to haue a fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and ſenſible touch of diuers well-diſpoſed yonge gentlewomen; who through the decay of their Parents ſtate, not hauing ſufficient portions left them to enter into Religion (being of themſelues otherwiſe moſt deſirous to ſhake handes for euer with the world, by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that courſe) are forced to forbeare that their moſt
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:3282:120"/> Religious inclination, &amp; for want of meanes to take ſome ſecular Courſe of life, either by mariage, or otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>Now here, how truly Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and Heroicall a part of Chriſtian Catholike Muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficene and bounty were it in you, by increaſing their Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to ſupply ſuch their wants, &amp; thereby to turne the channell of their other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous courſe? Which if you do performe, what haue you done? This you haue done. You haue cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a yong Gentle-woman (otherwiſe expoſed, &amp; lying open to the dangers of the
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:3282:121"/> world) to Cloyſter herſelfe within a wall, there to ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d all her lyfe tyme, in Chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Obedience, Voluntary pouerty, and other deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s; ryſing at midnight (to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare all other her auſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties) when your ſelues are taking your ſweet repoſe &amp; reſt, to ſing laudes to God, &amp; to pray for her benefactours, &amp; particularly for you, who haue beene the cauſe of ſuch her moſt happy choyce of life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhe thus by your charity increaſing the number of thoſe, <hi>qui ſequuntur agnum; quocumque inerit. Apoc.</hi> 14. Here is an Act deſeruing the <pb n="211" facs="tcp:3282:121"/> true name of Chriſtian cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and ſuch as ſhalbe able (through Gods moſt merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full acceptance therof) to arme the Soule againſt the Flames of <hi>Purgatory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to proceed to other ſorts of good Deeds, practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the forward Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> We ſee in moſt places of the Realme, that there are diuers earneſt Proteſtants, who ſeeing ſome neighbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring places wanting prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching Miniſters, are ready to plant ſuch men there; affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them large allowa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; this to the end, the more to dilate their owne Proteſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall <pb n="212" facs="tcp:3282:122"/> Fayth, ouer much all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſpread and diſſemina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. And hence it is, that ſo many Stipendary Miniſters are ſetled in ſeuerall places of the Realme. Now, why ſhould ſuch of you as be of greater ability, be inferiour in Zeale to the Proteſtants herein, as to ſuffer ſuch va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant places, as are neare to you, to be deſtitute of all ſuch inſtruments in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Faith? I doubt not but that diuers of you, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a peece of land cloſe by you, though rough and vntil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; yet of it owne Nature (through ſmal charges) moſt <pb n="213" facs="tcp:3282:122"/> fruitfull: I doubt not (I ſay) but that diuers of you would be deſirous, either to buy, or at leaſt to take a Leaſe of the ſaid land, therby to better your ſtates the more. There are diuers waſt places adioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to euery one of you, wherein liue many ciuill &amp; morall men, yet their vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtanding (in regard of any Religion) are but as
<hi>Tabulae Raſae,</hi> or vnmanured land.</p>
               <p>Now heere, what a moſt worthy and Chriſtian at<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tempt, and endeauour were it in you, to ſeeke to plant ſpirituall labourers in ſuch places, by whoſe paynes the <pb n="214" facs="tcp:3282:123"/> ſeed of Catholike Religion might be ſowne in mens ſoules; ſince the <hi>Georgikes</hi> of the mind (ſo to ſpeake) are far more worthy &amp; noble, then the
<hi>Georgikes</hi> or Agriculature of land? And would not then thoſe ſacred textes of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture here be verified of you: <hi>Seminanti iustitiam merces fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delis, Prou</hi> 11. <hi>He that ſoweth righteouſnes, receaueth a ſure reward:</hi> and againe: <hi>Qui opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur terram ſuam, inaltabit acer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uum frugum, Eccl.</hi> 20. <hi>Who til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth his land, ſhall increaſe his heape of Corne; to wit Heauenly Corne?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O what a ſpirituall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe <pb n="215" facs="tcp:3282:123"/> might ſuch of you make, who haue full and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen purſes, by cultiuating of diuers of theſe barre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> places? And how forcible would ſuch pious endeuours be, for the expiating of the relicks of your ſinnes? Therefore let not the Puritan Gentilmen, and others, exceed and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe you in their Zeale to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God (though <hi>Zeale not according to knowledg. Rom.</hi> 10.) in this point, who are moſt liberall in maintaining of their Preachers, and all to plant their Errours, to the ſpirituall Danger of the ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les of their credulous and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant <pb n="216" facs="tcp:3282:124"/> Hearers; But labour by ſecret meanes without conteſtation to the preſent ſtate (to which you ought euer to beare all duty and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence) to ſupererogate with them, in pious workes of this Nature.</p>
               <p>An other point, wherein we may well follow the ſteps of our Aduerſaries, is this. The Proteſtant Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men (though of very great worth and Ranke) do often ſend their yonger Sonnes to our Engliſh Vniuerſities, prouiding that they may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come fellowes of Houſes; whoſe <hi>Terminus ad quem</hi> (as I <pb n="217" facs="tcp:3282:124"/> may ſay) is finally to become Miniſters, and thereby to be promoted to great and rich Eccleſiaſticall liuings; in which ſtore and abundance, <hi>England</hi> exceedeth all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in Chriſtendome. Now to be emulous of our Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries proceeding herein: if Catholike Parents would ſeriouſly ponder this point, no doubt they would be more carefull and willing to ſend ouer their yonger ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to Catholike Colledges beyond the Seas, then they are; not to become ſchollars, only thereby to be aduanced to ſpirituall liuings (an ouer
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:3282:125"/> vnworthy Allectiue) but to become Prieſts, (that throgh ſheeding of their bloud) euen after an Apoſtolicall man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, they may labour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce their owne Country to its former ancient Catholike and Roman Fayth.</p>
               <p>Now, ſuch yonger Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of Catholikes, which haue not their education a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, but only bred vp in England; into what (for the moſt part) do they finally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue? They (for example) being left by their Parents Twenty, or Thirty, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps forty pounds Annuity (and ſometimes leſſe then, <pb n="219" facs="tcp:3282:125"/> any of theſe) what courſe do moſt of theſe after their parents deceaſe, vſually vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoe? To be in ſeruice to any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or Knight or Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of worth, or to be in any good employment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad for their temporall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement, many of them out of a long habituated id<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenes, and as being at their owne diſpoſall and liberty, will not. And what then commonly do they? For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth they reſt content with their owne poore Annuities, burdening commonly their Elder Brother (if he be a man of a good and kind Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) <pb n="220" facs="tcp:3282:126"/> for their diet; and they rauell out their yeares, wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vp and downe, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineiring among their El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Brothers Tenants and Neighbours, with a Marlin, or Sparhauke on their fiſt, &amp; a Grey-hound, or water ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell following them (the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry badge, or armes of moſt yonger Brothers in diuers Shyres) hiding themſelues for the moſt part of the day, in ſome baſe Ale-houſe; and often becomming (through diſſolution of life) Fathers, before they be Husbands. But in the end (belike for feare their Houſe, from <pb n="221" facs="tcp:3282:126"/> whence they deſcend, ſhould be extinct for wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Heires) they marry their Siſter-in-lawes wayting mayde, or ſome other poore woman, and then they beget a litter of Beggars, both burden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and diſhonorable to their Family and Stock.</p>
               <p>But now, if we caſt our eye vpon the other end of the ballance: Yf ſuch yonger ſonnes of Catholike Pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts (being of good wits) were ſent ouer in their Parents life time, and that when their minds and wills were of a ſupple and waxen Diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as not being acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:3282:127"/> afore (through want of yeares) with any ſinne or E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, and ready to receaue the impreſſion of Vertue &amp; lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; how ſeruiceable to the Church of God in tyme, might ſuch men become? For by this meanes of education, many of them do vndergoe (as we fynd by experience) a moſt holy Function of life; ſpending their whole age af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, in laboring to adminiſter the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of the Church to Catholikes, in reducing diuers Proteſtants to the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly true and Catholike Fayth, and in daily praying &amp; offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vp the moſt Venerable <pb n="223" facs="tcp:3282:127"/> Sacrifice of Chriſtes body, for the ſoules of their dead Parents, and others their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing or deceaſed Friends. <hi>O quantum diſtat ortus ab occaſu?</hi> for ſo great is the Diſparity betweene theſe two differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t courſes of Yonger Brothers here ſet downe; not only in the eye of God, but euen in the eye of the world.</p>
               <p>And heere by digreſſion I will touch a little vpon the Daughters of Catholicke Gentle-men. Heere in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> diuers of them (as well as the Daughters of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants) take (throgh a blind affection, often caſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome <pb n="224" facs="tcp:3282:128"/> baſe man or other) a moſt vnworthy Courſe, to the vnutterable griefe of their Parents, and ouerthrow of their temporall ſtate. And if they be placed in mariage with their Parents conſent anſwerably to their Degree; yet if either the Husbands proue vnkind, or in courſe of life vitious; or their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren vntoward and licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, what a vexation is it then to the Parents? And how do they languiſhingly ſpend their dayes in inconſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable ſighs and ſorrow?</p>
               <p>But now, if the ſaid Daughters, being in their
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:3282:128"/> Virginall, tender, and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent age, be brought vp in places of Religion, and that through the ſpeciall grace of God, and meanes of ther dai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly education, they proceed and become Religious wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in the Church of God; How ineffable a comfort may this be to their Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like parents? Since they then by theſe meanes, freeing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues from all illaquea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and worldly entangle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſhall beſtow the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part both of Day and Night in performing, &amp; ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Hymnes of Prayſes to his Diuine Maieſty, for the <pb n="226" facs="tcp:3282:129"/> good of themſelues &amp; their Friends: To euery one of which, at the Cloſe of their lyfe may be ſaid in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke Churches <hi>Dialect: Veni ſponſa Chriſti, accipe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronam, quam tibi Dominus prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parauit in aeternum. (in Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect. Natalit. Virg.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus far of this point. And I would to God, that Catholicke Parents would apprehend this Paragraph or paſſage with a ſerious &amp; fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling conſideration. And thus far of theſe former Courſes, in imitating the examples of our Aduerſaries; which exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples were moſt worthy of <pb n="227" facs="tcp:3282:129"/> all commendation, being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated in an Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxall Religion. But yet heere, in our Imitation of them, I euer wiſh, that what is attempted in this kind (or els not to be attempted) were performed (as before I intimated) with all ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and moderation, and withall dutifull Reſpect to the ſtate of our Realme. Since I hould it moſt repugnant to true Iudgment &amp; Religion, to vndertake to put in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe orderly things, by vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly meanes; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in all ſuch our ſpirituall endeauours let vs remember, <pb n="228" facs="tcp:3282:130"/> to ſhew all duty and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the State, and that it is recorded in ſacred Writ, (<hi>Rom.</hi> 13.) <hi>We are to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to higher powers; ſeeing there is no power, but of God.</hi> And there againe: <hi>Who reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steth the Power, reſisteth the Ordinance of God.</hi> In regard of which promptnes of our duty, I hope theſe examples, as being taken by imitation from the Proteſtants them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, will not be iuſtly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſiue to the graue Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Magiſtrate.</p>
               <p>There is yet another thing moſt worthy of your chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table commiſeration. You <pb n="229" facs="tcp:3282:130"/> ſee, that the Catholickes throughout England pay yerely great ſommes of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney for their Recuſancy; A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong whom, there are many hundred of poore Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, who are ſo ouerchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with theſe yearely pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as that their meane Eſtates are not able to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port any long time ſuch pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; of which his Maieſty (who is moſt prone to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeration and pitty) litle heareth in particular; this being effected only by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Subordinate Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, aduerſe to our Catholike Religion. And thereupon <pb n="230" facs="tcp:3282:131"/> for their auoiding of the ſaid payments, impoſed vpon them, diuers of theſe poore men and women haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken already (contrary to their conſcience) externally their Religion, and are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to come to the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Church.</p>
               <p>Now heere I ſay, ſuch of you, as be of great Abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, how ample a field haue you to ſow your merits and ſatisfactions in; I meane by contributing out of your purſes ſome yearly ſommes to theſe poore Catholikes, thereby to eaſe, and leſſen their yearely payments? In
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:3282:131"/> your worthy performa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of this my propounded Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, you do not only help and ſuccour them touching their bodies; but (which is far more pleaſing in the ſight of God,) you ſo take pitty of their ſoules, as you preuent, that diuers of them do not Apoſtatate &amp; forſake their Catholicke Religion, which perhaps throgh feare of want of meanes they would doe; And ſo you are become a ſecondary great Inſtrument of their finall Saluation.</p>
               <p>And can you then other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe thinke, but that God
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:3282:132"/> (who is mercy it ſelfe) and who will take this Charity of yours as done to himſelfe, would take the like pitty of your owne ſoules, both for the preuenting of your eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall perdition, as alſo for mitigating your temporall puniſhments in Purgatory? For heer our Sauiours words would be iuſtified in you, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. <hi>Verily I ſay vnto you, in ſo much as you haue don<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne it vnto one of the least of theſe my brethren, you haue done it vnto me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this next place, I will deſcend to acts peculiar on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to vs Catholikes; &amp; ſuch <pb n="233" facs="tcp:3282:132"/> as do inſiſt, and reſt in offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vp the prayers both of our ſelues, but eſpecially of the generall Liturgy of the moſt bleſſed Sacrifice of the Euchariſt, offered vp either for the benefit of our ſelues, or of others. Of which moſt dreadfull Sacrifice ſayth <hi>S. Chryſostome homil.</hi> 25. <hi>in Act. Apoſt. Hostia in manibus, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt Angeli, adſunt Archan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geli, adeſt Filius Dei, cum tanto horrore aſtant omnes.</hi> And to begin; Thinke what a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, and charitable Act it were to concurre by cauſing Sacrifices and Prayers to be made, for the redeeming of <pb n="234" facs="tcp:3282:133"/> poore Soules out of <hi>Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is no man of an Humane and ſweet Nature, but he would commiſerate a very beaſt (much more a man) lying in extremity of paynes. And this Naturall Pitty is ſo gratefull to our Sauiour himſelfe, as that he pronounceth, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. <hi>Beati miſericordes, quoniam ipſi miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordiam conſequentur; Bleſſed are the mercifull, for they ſhall obtayne mercy:</hi> So auaylable &amp; behooffull is pitty and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to the performers thereof. But to proceed to another benefit of ſuch a pious deed.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="235" facs="tcp:3282:133"/>Yf a prudent man, had a Cauſe of moſt great impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, to be tryed before a ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uere, yet moſt iuſt Iudge; And if at the ſame tyme, there were certaine perſons in priſon, whom that Iudge did much reſpect, &amp; to whoſe earneſt ſolicitations in any reaſonable point, he would lend a willing eare: Now would not this Suppliant lay wayte by all meanes to redeeme the ſaid men out of Priſon, if ſo he could (who during their ſtay there, were put to daily torments and rackings) as well aſſuring himſelfe, that theſe Perſons <pb n="236" facs="tcp:3282:134"/> thus ſet at liberty by this mans meanes (being men of moſt good and gratefull Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures &amp; Diſpoſitions) would be ready to ſpeake to the Iudge, and be earneſt and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitous in his behalfe? And then is it not moſt probable (if not certaine) that this man would ſpeed the better in determining his Cauſe?</p>
               <p>The caſe is here a like, and both are caſt (as it were) in one mould. The ſoules in <hi>Purgatory</hi> (once from thence releaſed) ſhall become moſt bleſſed Saints in Heauen, &amp; ſhall be moſt pleaſing and gratefull to his Diuine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty; <pb n="237" facs="tcp:3282:134"/> who cannot, nor will not deny them the grant of any thing, which they ſhall demaund, and petition for at his hands.</p>
               <p>Euery Catholike (as all other men) are to plead their cauſe before God, the moſt iuſt Iudge: Yet for the more eaſy obtayning of their Plea, it is in the power of ech Catholike of good meanes (if his will be anſwerable thereto) to procure, at leaſt much to further, by his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall charges beſtowed for the praying for the ſoules in <hi>Purgatory,</hi> the releaſing and ſetting free of diuers of the <pb n="238" facs="tcp:3282:135"/> ſaid tormented ſoules.</p>
               <p>Now this being once per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, thoſe then Happy Soules, ſhall no ſooner leaue their Goale and Priſon, and aſcend to Heauen; but as euen abounding with a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphicall Charity, ſhall in recompe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of ſo great a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall eaſe and Relaxation procured to them, euer bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter at the eares of our Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty and mercifull Lord, with their daily and inceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant prayers; that his Diuine Mercy would be moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgent and pittifull to ſuch men, for the preuenting (or at leaſt mitigating) of their
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:3282:135"/> temporall paynes, by whoſe meanes thoſe ſoules had a more ſpeedy deliuery from their torments in <hi>Purgatory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Heere then may a man, who is rich in temporall ſtate (if ſo he be rich in cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity) lay out his wealth to an infinite increaſe of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall gayne. O how many peculiar <hi>Aduocates</hi> and
<hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſours</hi> of the then moſt bleſſed ſoules (releaſed out of <hi>Purgatory</hi>) might a rich Catholike purchaſe to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, by this former meanes, thereby to pleade his cauſe before the Throne of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, in his greateſt <pb n="240" facs="tcp:3282:136"/> need? And fooles (I will not ſay Madmen) are all ſuch, vpon whom God hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed abundance of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall riches; and yet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues remayne vnwilling &amp; ſlow in this ſpirituall traffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que of a good and compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent part of their ſaid tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſtate and meanes.</p>
               <p>But becauſe this point of relieuing by <hi>Good Workes</hi> the ſoules in <hi>Purgatory,</hi> is of moſt great importance, both to the poore ſoules relieued, &amp; the liuing party performing ſuch a moſt charitable work to them: Therefore beſydes what is already deliuered
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:3282:136"/> by me aboue, I will adioyne (as moſt mouing any man of Piety and Iudgment) the diſcourſe of the aforemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned learned and worthy
<hi>Cardinall Bellarmine</hi> of this point; who maketh the ninth Chapter of the third booke <hi>de Gemitu Columbae,</hi> the ſubiect hereof: Thus then that bleſſed man writeth: <hi>We haue ſhewed aboue, that there are very many, or rather innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable ſoules of the faithfull in Purgatory; and that they are a most long tyme to be tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, almoſt with incredible pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments. Now here we will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the fruite, which may be
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:3282:137"/> gathered from this conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And certainly it cannot be doubted, but if the pondera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and weighing of this point be ſerious, longe, attent, and full of fayth and confidence; a most vehement commiſeration, and full of horrour and feare will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult out of the ſaid conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And in like ſort it is certaine, that an earnest and intenſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the ſaid point, will ingender in vs a vehement de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of helping the ſaid ſoules in Purgatory, by ſatisfactory workes; to wit, Prayer, Faſting, Almes-deeds, and chiefly by the most holy oblation, and Sacrifice <pb n="243" facs="tcp:3282:137"/> of our Lords body. And indeed it is most admirable to obſerue, how gainfull a negotiation (and this most iust) may accrew vnto vs thereby. And this ſpirituall negotiation may well be reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to the proceeding of a man, who ſhould deliuer one and the ſame ſiluer (vpon vſury) to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall Merchants; and yet ſhould receaue a full and entyre Interest for one and the ſaid Siluer, from euery one of the Merchants.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let vs explayne our ſelues in few words. A man prayeth for the Dead, attentiuely, piouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, with fayth, and great confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of impetration and obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <pb n="244" facs="tcp:3282:138"/> the thing prayed for. This man ſo praying, by way of merit purchaſeth to himſelfe the gayne of eternall felicity and happines: ſince Prayer is a good worke, &amp; in that reſpect deſeruing eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life, if it proceed from Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. Of which gayne our Lord ſpeaketh in the Ghoſpell in theſe words, Matth.</hi> 6.
<hi>Tu autem cum oraueris &amp;c. Thou, when thou ſhalt pray, enter into thy chamber, and hauing ſhut the doore, pray to thy Father in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret; and thy Father, who ſeeth thee in ſecret, will repay thee; To wit, a Reward anſwerable to the merit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Furthermore, this praying <pb n="245" facs="tcp:3282:138"/> for the Dead, by way of ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, doth profit the departed ſoule in Purgatory, for the which it is performed: ſeeing Prayer is (amongſt others) a laborious worke, and therein it is ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory; and conſequently it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for that ſoule, to which it is applyed, according to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of him that prayeth, &amp; the Doctrine of the Church. To conclude by way of impetration and humbly begging, it profiteth the ſaid departed ſoule, whoſe freeing from Purgatory, at least whoſe eaſe and mitigation of thoſe paynes, is therin beſeeched and deſired. Since that, for which Iust men pray to God, <pb n="246" facs="tcp:3282:139"/> through Christ, is eaſely obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: Our Lord himſelfe ſaying Luc.</hi> 11. <hi>Petite, &amp; accipietis &amp;c. Aske, and you ſhall receaue: and againe, Marc.</hi> 11.
<hi>Quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid orantes, petitis &amp;c. All things whatſoeuer you aske, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, belieue that you shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue, and they ſhall come vnto you. And more, Ioan.</hi> 16. <hi>Si quid petieritis &amp;c. Yf you aske the Father any thing in my name, he ſhall giue it you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Behould heere a threefould gayne, proceeding from prayer, made in behalfe of the ſoules de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted. But there may be adioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a fourth benefit: That is, the ſoules, for which we pray, <pb n="247" facs="tcp:3282:139"/> will not be vngratefull, when they ſhall arriue into their hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Country; but shall anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>were &amp; recompence our prayers, with their like prayers in our behalfe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To proceed; Fasting being performed by vs, and applyed for the deceaſed, obtayneth a mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fould gaine. For first, (as a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious worke) it is profitable to him, who fasteth, euen by the testimony of our Lord himſelfe Matth.</hi> 6. <hi>Tu autem, cum ieiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas, &amp;c. When thou dost fast, annoynt thy head, and waſh thy face, that thou appeare not to men to faſt, but to thy Father, which is in ſecret; and thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="248" facs="tcp:3282:140"/> which ſeeth in ſecret, will repay thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fasting alſo, as a ſatisfactory worke, being applyed for the dead, doth helpe the dead. For not without iust cauſe, did Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid fast, with all his retinue and trayne euen till night, when he was aduertized of the ouerthrow of King</hi> Saul, <hi>and</hi> Ionathas, <hi>and of a great part of the people of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To conclude, Faſting (in an other manner) profiteth the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſo faſting; to wit, in that the ſoules of the departed, when they shall aſcend to Heauen, will not be forgetfull of their Benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours; but will power out prayers <pb n="249" facs="tcp:3282:140"/> for them; and ſuch their prayers, as proceeding from true Charity, ſhall be heard.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now, in this next place, to come to Almes-deeds. This kind of good Worke alſo is accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with a threefould gayne. For first, it profiteth the poore, to which the Almes-deeds are giuen, and maketh them to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come our friends, that ſo when we fayle, they may receaue vs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to eternall Tabernacles. Luc.</hi> 16. <hi>Againe, Almes-deeds being applyed for the vſe of the ſoules departed, do bring a refreſhing and refocillation to the ſaid ſoules; and conſequently make them alſo to become our friends, <pb n="250" facs="tcp:3282:141"/> who hauing a title to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heauen, will no doubt helpe vs with their holy Prayers and Interceſsions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly, Almes-deeds do (as I may ſay) bynd God to be a deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour vnto vs; for thus the Holy Ghost ſpeaketh by the mouth of Salomon: Qui miſeretur paupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, foeneratur Domino: Who ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth pitty of the poore, doth put out his ſiluer to intereſt, euen to our Lord. Prou.</hi> 19.
<hi>And Christ confirmeth the ſame in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, ſaying, Matth.</hi>
6. <hi>Te fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciente Eleemoſynam &amp;c. When thou dost an Almes deed, let not thy left hand know, what thy right hand doth, that thy Almes-deed
<pb n="251" facs="tcp:3282:141"/> may be ſecret, and thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which ſeeth in ſecret, will repay thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To deſcend to the most bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sacrifice of Christs body &amp; bloud; It is most cleare and eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that that oblation profiteth the party, who offereth it vp, as a guift most gratefull to God: It profiteth the faithfull liuing, as alſo the faithfull ſoules de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted. And that this is most vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly true, appeareth from the many most credible Viſions or apparitions, manifeſting that the faithfull ſoules in Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, do deſire and expect nothing more, then that the most cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stiall oblation of the body and <pb n="252" facs="tcp:3282:142"/> bloud of Chriſt may be offered vp for their refreſhing, or free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them from their paynes. Of which point read S. Gregory lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Dialogorum. cap.</hi> 75. <hi>&amp; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent. Alſo the History of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland writen by Venerable Bede lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi>
13.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In like ſort the Epiſtle of Petrus Damianus ad Deſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium, may be read; &amp; finally the lyfe of S. Nicolaus Tolentinus in Surius tom.</hi> 5. <hi>ad diem</hi> 10. <hi>Septembris: For to this bleſsed Priest appeared once a great multitude of ſoules, who with teares and most lachrimall voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces deſired of him the celebration of the moſt holy Sacrifice, as a <pb n="253" facs="tcp:3282:142"/> principall Remedy for their pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in Purgatory. Now from all the Premiſſes, it is euident, that we may receaue a most preciable and incomparable gayne, if we daily powre out our prayers, for the ſoules departed; or if we do diſtribute Almes to the poore, for the eaſe and refreſhment of their paynes; or if we do ſatisfy for the ſaid ſoules, either by our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, or other penitential works; or finally do celebrate the most holy Sacrifice of the Maſſe for their deliuery out of Purgatory.</hi> Thus far learned <hi>Bellarmine</hi> diſcourſeth of this point. Whoſe words I would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire euery good Catholicke
<pb n="254" facs="tcp:3282:143"/> Reader ſeriouſly to obſerue.</p>
               <p>But to enlarge my ſelfe a little further, I could wiſh all of you of good ſtates, when iuſt occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is preſented, that you would be moſt bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in relieuing impriſoned Prieſts, and poore impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Catholiks. O how wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy an Act is this, and how do you ſuffer in their ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings? And you may then infallibly intereſt your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues in the words of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6. <hi>God is not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iust, that he can forget your good workes, and charity, which you haue shewed in his name, and haue, and do minister vnto <pb n="255" facs="tcp:3282:143"/> his Saints.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I well remember, that ſome twenty yeares ſince, a certaine Priſon hauing in it ſome ſix or ſeauen Prieſts, &amp; far more poore lay Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, lying there in great want; there was a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like gentle woman of good account, who taking great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſeration of their wants, relieued all the Catholike impriſoned company, with weekly prouiſion of meate for ſeuerall months; and ſo ſhe intended ſtill to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue this her Charity, but that ſhe was ſhortly after preuented by death. This was
<pb n="256" facs="tcp:3282:144"/> an Heroicall and moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian charity in her, able no doubt (throgh Chriſts mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull acceptance thereof) euen to abate the flames of <hi>Purgatory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In like ſort, I could wiſh all of you, who are carefull to preuent the raging flames or <hi>Purgatory,</hi> that what workes of labour, or ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, or Almes deeds you inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to doe, that you would not defer the accompliſhing of them, till the day of your departure out of this world; but performe them when you are in health. The diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is moſt great betweene
<pb n="257" facs="tcp:3282:144"/> a worke of Charity done at the Houre of a mans death, and when he is in health not likely to dye.</p>
               <p>For in the firſt manner, the party dying, giueth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his goods to pious vſes, becauſe he cannot enioy them any longer. In the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, it is in a mans power to keep his riches longer, &amp; yet departing from them in his Health, he is content thereby actually to leſſen in his owne daies his temporall meanes, and departeth with them with cherefulnes and alacrity of mind; a circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance moſt pleaſing to God,
<pb n="258" facs="tcp:3282:145"/> ſince we read) 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. <hi>Hila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem datorem diligit Deus; God loueth a chearfull giuer.</hi> In the former, the will of a dying man is not (for the moſt part) in all things perfor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med, either through the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſnes of the wife, Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, or negligence of the Executors: In this other, a man is aſſured his will ſhall be performed; ſince he is re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſolued to make his owne <hi>Hands,</hi> his
<hi>Executors,</hi> and his owne <hi>Eyes,</hi> his <hi>Ouerſeers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, Almes-deeds do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne after the firſt ſort, do take ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect only at the death of the Party &amp; not before; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
<pb n="259" facs="tcp:3282:145"/> they being diſtributed af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter this ſecond ſort, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to worke and obtaine by degrees Indulge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, leſſening of the future paynes, euen from that houre, in which they were firſt beſtowed: So great a diſparity there is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weene hauing a Candell go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before a man, lighting him the way to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heauen, &amp; hauing a Candell only to follow him.</p>
               <p>I am perſuaded, there are very few of you ſo ſimple, who if you did owe great ſummes of Money, and were infallibly to pay euery pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them, if other courſe <pb n="260" facs="tcp:3282:146"/> in the meane tyme could not be taken; But that if by preuention of time (I meane by paying afore the day of payment co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth) you might be ſuffered in lieu of the whole, to pay but the twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tith part, and thereby to be diſcharged of the whole great debt; but that you would take courſe by all meanes poſſible (yea by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king your ſiluer vp at Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt) for the preſent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of the ſaid twentith part, ſo to redeeme your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues from the payment of all the reſt. I do aſſure you euen from the teſtimonies of all
<pb n="261" facs="tcp:3282:146"/> ancient &amp; learned Fathers, that it is in your power to redeeme not only the twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tith part of your future tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in Purgatory, but euen the greateſt part, and perhaps all, by your charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Deeds, liberality, and pious workes, now done in your life time: And will you then be ſlow in taking the like courſe herein? <hi>O in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſati Galatae, quis vos faſcina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit? Gal.</hi> 3. But I will yet go further with you.</p>
               <p>There are not many of you (I ſpeake of ſuch of you as are much deuoted to the world) but that, if you had <pb n="262" facs="tcp:3282:147"/> a fayre demayne of fiue hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pounds yearely worth, though not in poſſeſſion; yet that it were infallibly to deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend to you and your Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity for euer, after twenty yeares were expired: And that notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding it were in your Power &amp; Freedome, to buy out and redeeme the ſaid twenty yeares, thereby to haue preſent poſſeſſion of it; I ſay, there are not many of you, but that you would ſtriue, though it were by impoueriſhing your ſelues for the tyme, and by liuing vnder your owne worth, thereby to procure meanes <pb n="263" facs="tcp:3282:147"/> for the redeeming of the ſaid terme of twenty yeares.</p>
               <p>Heauen is your Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, after the guilt of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall damnation is once re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted; Yet thither it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for you to arriue, vntil for certaine yeares you haue performed your tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall puniſhments yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining. Theſe inexplicable puniſhments, which may endure for many ſcores of yeares, more then twenty, (yea it may be for ſeuerall hundreds of yeares) you may redeeme perhaps for leſſe charges to your Purſe, diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>burſed in your life time and <pb n="264" facs="tcp:3282:148"/> health to pious &amp; religious vſes (through Chriſts moſt mercifull acceptance,) then you would be content to lay out, for the getting in of the former mentioned twenty yeares. And yet how Dull, and Backward are moſt of you to vndertake the ſame? How can you heere Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gize or excuſe your ſelues? Is Heauen not ſo good, as an earthly demaine? O men of little Fayth! What a muddy diſpoſition of the Soule is this, which lyes ſo groueling vpon the earth, and wholy abſorpt in terrene thoughts and cogitations?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="265" facs="tcp:3282:148"/>Well, ceaſing to enlarge my ſelfe further vpon the Premiſſes, I earneſtly deſire euery one of you, to procure now in tyme of Health, the moſt Reuerend &amp; Dreadfull Sacrifice of the moſt bleſſed body and bloud of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour to be offered daily vp, to two ends; to wit, for the ſpirituall good of your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues and your Children; and ſecondly, for the preuenting of your future paines of
<hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory.</hi> And that you ſhall perceaue of what ineffable vertue and efficacy for mans ſoule, the offering vp of that moſt dreadfull Sacrifice is, I <pb n="266" facs="tcp:3282:149"/> haue thought good to ſet downe the Iudgmentes of ſome few ancient Fathers, pretermitting the greateſt part of them, for greater bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uity.</p>
               <p>Firſt then we find <hi>S. Cyrill of Alexandria Epist<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ad Nestor.</hi> to write, that by meanes of this daily Sacrifice, <hi>We are made partakers of the holy body and precious bloud of Christ. S. Austin</hi> calleth the ſaid Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, <hi>Precium nostrum, Our pryce. Confeſſ. cap.</hi>
13. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſame Father thus writeth <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>de Trinit. cap.</hi> 14. <hi>Quid gratius offerri &amp;c. What can be offered vp, or accepted <pb n="267" facs="tcp:3282:149"/> more thankefully, then that the fleſh of our Sacrifice, ſhould be come the body of our Prieſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S. Chryſostome</hi> thus tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, <hi>Homil.</hi> 21.
<hi>in Act. Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolorum. Hostia in manibus &amp;c. The ſacred hoſt being in the hands of the Prieſt, the Angels are preſent, the Archangels are preſent, the ſonne of God is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, cum tanto horrore astant omnes, with ſo much feare and horrour all of them are preſent. S. Gregory Nyſsene</hi> thus expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly writeth, <hi>Orat. Cathech. c.</hi> 36.
<hi>Fidelium corporibus &amp;c. That body</hi> (meaning the body of) Chriſt in the Sacrifice of the Maſſe) <hi>is ioyned with the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies
<pb n="268" facs="tcp:3282:150"/> of the faythfull, that by the coniunction of the immortall body, man may be made partaker of immortality. S. Cyprian</hi> thus teacheth of the offering vp of the body, and bloud of Chriſt in the holy Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt <hi>(Serm. de coena Dom.) Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes eſt hoc ſacrificium &amp;c. This is a daily Sacrifice, and is a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent or perpetuall Holocaust.</hi> To conclude the foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned <hi>S. Chryſoſtome</hi> thus writeth
<hi>(hom.</hi> 2. <hi>in</hi> 1. <hi>ad Cor.) Dum in hac vita ſumus &amp;c. Whiles we are in this life, this mistery of the Euchariſt maketh, that the earth it ſelfe, is a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="269" facs="tcp:3282:150"/>And now hauing ſhewed out of the teſtimonies of the ancient Fathers, the impre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciable efficacy and vertue of the moſt Reuerend Sacrifice of Chriſts body and bloud, for the ſpirituall good of mans Soule; we may from thence conclude, that the daily offering vp of the ſaid moſt dreadfull Sacrifice (co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the worth of him there ſacrificed) is moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaylable &amp; behoofull, both for the ſoules of men yet li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, thereby to arme and ſtrengthen them with grace, againſt all the temptations of the World and the diuell; <pb n="270" facs="tcp:3282:151"/> as alſo for the expiating of mans Sinnes in <hi>Purgatory.</hi> Sweet Ieſus! no other impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tration, or prayer is more piercing in the eares of God, then this; ſince heere (for remitting of our ſinnes, and regulating our actions for the tyme hereafter with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine grace) the <hi>Sonne</hi> plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to the
<hi>Father, God</hi> to <hi>God;</hi> And the ſame man, is both the
<hi>Priest,</hi> and the <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yea this moſt Reuerend Myſtery of the Sacrifice of the
<hi>Maſſe,</hi> is the very center of Religion, and hart of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion; by meanes whereof <pb n="271" facs="tcp:3282:151"/> his diuine Maieſty moſt bountifully imparteth, and powreth out his fauours and graces to our ſoules: So cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and infallible it is, that our Prayers made in Vnion of this diuine Sacrifice (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for our ſpirituall good during our Peregrination in this world, or for the taking away of the paines of <hi>Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory,</hi>) haue an inexplicable power and efficacy: And therfore thoſe men are great Enemies to themſelues, and their Children, who neglect this ſo ſoueraigne a meanes, both for their owne &amp; their Childrens aduancement in <pb n="272" facs="tcp:3282:152"/> ſanctity and Vertue</p>
               <p>Yet before I end this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, I muſt adioyne this enſuing Animaduerſion; that whereas moſt of the former examples of
<hi>Good Workes</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue alledged, &amp; inſtanced, aime at great &amp; high points; ſorting only to ſuch to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, whoſe temporall ſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes are great and rich, and to whom that admonition of <hi>S. Chryſostome</hi> (aboue alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged) peculiarly belongeth, <hi>Non dare, ſed copiosè dare Elee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſyna eſt:</hi> Neuertheleſſe we are to conceaue, that the Charity of ſuch, as be but poore in temporall faculties <pb n="273" facs="tcp:3282:152"/> though, neuer ſo ſmall, are moſt pleaſing to his diuine Maieſty, for the mitigating of the torments of <hi>Purgatory.</hi> And in this ſenſe we muſt vnderſtand, that euen the poore <hi>Widdow</hi> in the Ghoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, who had but two mites, gaue as much as <hi>Zachaeus,</hi> who contributed the halfe of his great ſubſtance to the poore; becauſe, though the widdow had leſſer goods to giue, yet ſhe had the like will of giuing; And though, that which was ſeuerally giuen by them both, were vnequall &amp; diuers; yet the fountaine from whence they gaue (to
<pb n="274" facs="tcp:3282:153"/> wit from a prompt and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable diſpoſition of relie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the poore) was the ſame. And thus did it fall out, that whereas the whole <hi>Widowes</hi> ſtate was but ſmall, yet the part thereof giuen, was great; <hi>Since he giueth no litle, who freely and cheerefully giueth a part of a little.</hi> And therefore the foreſaid <hi>S. Chryſostome</hi> accordingly thus teacheth <hi>(Hom.</hi> 34. <hi>ad pop. Antioch.) Eleemoſinae magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudo, non in pecuniarum multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudine iudicatur, ſed in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> promptitudine.</hi> With whom accordeth <hi>S. Leo (ſer.</hi> 4.
<hi>de Quadrag.)</hi> ſaying, <hi>Ex affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus <pb n="275" facs="tcp:3282:153"/> piorum, benignitatis menſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra taxatur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Well, I will cloſe vp this ſmall Treatiſe with refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Catholicke Reader, to the practiſe of a ſkillfull Phiſitian, who can extract medicinable and healthfull Phyſick, out of hurtfull and venemous drugs or hearbs: So heere I moſt earneſtly wiſh, that all good Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes (according to the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent proportion of their ſtates and power) would in their owne life time, (for the preuenting or leſſening of the torments of <hi>Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi>) put in daily practiſe that
<pb n="276" facs="tcp:3282:154" rendition="simple:additions"/> counſell of our Sauiour: <hi>Luc.</hi> 16.
<hi>Facite vobis amicos de Mammona iniquitatis, vt cum defeceritis, recipiant vos in ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terna tabernacula. Make you friends of the Mammon of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, that when you fayle, they may receaue you into eternall Tabernacles.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <closer>God ſaue the King.</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:3282:154" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
